<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[SHIQI's Blog]]></title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-16T16:10:22.000Z</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SHIQI]]></name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[PlantPeace - A Peaceful Living Space]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2018/01/16/portfolio6/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2018/01/16/portfolio6/</id>
    <published>2018-01-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:10:22.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes a noise management system that helps students (noise suffers and noisemakers) who lives in student accommodation to deal with noise issues. Welcome to any comments : )<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/PlantPeace.png" alt="PlantPeace" title="PlantPeace"></p>
<p>There is also an introduction video about PlantPeace (P.S. If you live in China, you might need VPN to watch the following video)</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mF0U2w5V3f8" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The porfolio got the distinction mark, here is the individual feedback from <a href="https://uclic.ucl.ac.uk/people/nicolai-marquardt" target="_blank" rel="external">Nicolai Marquardt</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Excellent quality of presented portfolio; great to see variety of design methods. Very high quality portfolio design, with a clear structure and layout. Very refined sketches and visual mockups. Great to see sampling of a larger design space (the sketches on page 4 were great, but some of them a bit difficult to see). Excellent wireframes! You could possibly improve some of the descriptions of your designs, by better explaining the function of a design, what is shown and how it works (e.g., the storyboard or wireframe on page 4, or the wireframes on page 5). It would be good to more explicitly describe the criteria for selecting designs and/or methods.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, if you want to know more about the PlantPeace Project, you can click here and find more details in the <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1atqw-PG3zBPLzxM2hubm61ITZzChPCcl/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="external">report</a>.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes a noise management system that helps students (noise suffers and noisemakers) who lives in student accommodation to deal with noise issues. Welcome to any comments : )]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[DeeperTrip - A Deeper Insight into Scenic Spot]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2018/01/15/portfolio5/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2018/01/15/portfolio5/</id>
    <published>2018-01-15T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-17T19:11:55.671Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes an AR product that helps users get a deeper insight of the culture and history of scenic spots. Welcome to any comments : )<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/DeeperTrip.png" alt="DeeperTrip" title="DeeperTrip"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes an AR product that helps users get a deeper insight of the culture and history of scenic spots. Welcome to any comments : )]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Exploring the Use of Virtual Assistants in a Restaurant]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/12/25/hci2/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/12/25/hci2/</id>
    <published>2017-12-25T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:12:22.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This proposal introduces an experimental method to manage recommendation and explore the use of virtual assistants in the context of a restaurant, and got a distinction mark.<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<h3 id="Introduction">Introduction</h3><p>“Hey Siri, find me a restaurant.” “OK, here is what I found,” said Siri, with a search engine results page presented. This conversation is a common scene for those who use virtual assistants (VA) in their daily lives. Defined as “an artificial agent that simulates a human assistant and prompts users to provide feedback by asking questions” (Ozeki, Maeda, Obata &amp; Nakamura, 2009), VAs are expected to become the next generation of Human Computer Interaction (HCI). Vying to lead this new generation of HCI, numerous enterprises are developing virtual assistants, such as Google Now, Amazon’s Alexa, Apple’s Siri and Facebook M. These virtual assistants innovate HCI as dialogue-style interactions, and allow users to access numerous services, such as launching apps, making phone calls, reading messages, playing music and others (Lee &amp; Choi, 2017; Rong, Fourney, Brewer, Morris &amp; Bennett, 2017).</p>
<p>Amongst these functionalities, recommendation is an existing feature of a few virtual assistants. To date, there is a wide range of literature resources. Most of the studies focus on certain aspects of virtual assistants’ recommendations, such as self-disclosure and reciprocity (Lee &amp; Choi, 2017). However, limited literature regards the virtual assistants’ recommendation as an independent factor and explores its effect on user performance (satisfaction, error, efforts) in different contexts. Neither did these researchers study user expectations when being recommended by virtual assistants. Therefore, in this proposal, both a quantitative study and a qualitative study are proposed for solving these two problems. The quantitative study looks at the effects of virtual assistants’ recommendations on user performance when users have different intentions. In other words, if the users have clear goals in mind. The qualitative study analyses the expectations that users have when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants. The quantitative study results can inspire interaction design by suggesting when it is a suitable circumstance for virtual assistants to recommend users<br>more options. The qualitative study results can help refine current design by considering the user expectations that have not been met. This proposal focuses on a scene where people use virtual assistants to select restaurants. This is to avoid the influence of confounding factors in other complicated scenes such as booking a flight or requesting an Uber ride. Accordingly, the proposal will be structured around answering the following two research questions: </p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Intention &amp; Recommendation Structure: Whether there is an effect of the user intention and the recommendation structure on the user performance (satisfaction, effort, error) when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    Expectation: What are users’ expectations when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants in different intentions?</em></p>
<p>Given the two research questions above, the study will employ a mixture of methods. The first research question is studied by designing a mixed factorial experiment, which will be followed by a mixed design Analysis of Variance (ANOVA). Regarding user expectations, a semi-structured interview is designed before employing grounded theory to investigate the totality of this context. Afterwards, the merits and demerits of these studies will be discussed.</p>
<h3 id="Literature_Review">Literature Review</h3><p>A number of related literature exists on the topic of virtual assistants. Crestani and Du (2006) claim that spoken queries on mobile searches are longer but more “natural”. This finding showed the potential of dialogue-style interactions. Furthermore, a wide range of research focuses on the use of virtual assistants, including the feature of recommendations. Smyth et al. (2004) studied how to rely on user preference and needs to automatically generate compound critiques that can be presented to the user, whereas Matejka et al. (2009) researched the algorithms and succeeded in increasing the number of good recommendations by 2.1 times. </p>
<p>However, little work involves user intention and the recommendation effects on user performance. An exception is Kang et al. (2017), who investigated how users deploy natural language to ask for recommendations. In this study, the taxonomy was employed and the user goals were divided into three levels: navigational, informational and transactional. The follow-up queries were applied and surprisingly, the finding showed that the user employed a ‘critiquing style’ when refining the initial request. Additionally, the users were more likely to query with deep features when speaking as opposed to texting. This indicated the imperfection of current systems and the potential of the conversational assistant. Similarly, Chai et al. (2002) compared the menu-driven system with the natural language system, and found that the number of clicks and average time were reduced by 63.2 percent and 33.3 percent respectively – the efficiency and promise of the natural language system were demonstrated in the research.</p>
<p>Regarding user intention, Lee and Choi (2017) proposed the research question as “How does self-disclosure and reciprocity between a user and a conversational assistant affect user satisfaction and intention to use?”. He found that self-disclosure and reciprocity were paramount factors that affect user satisfaction. Furthermore, the interactional enjoyment and the feeling of trust would make the recommendations more believable and persuasive. Although the above factors can lead to intention to use, the study lacks the research on the original intention of users. Therefore, in this proposal, the effects of user goals and recommendation structures will be discussed. The methods of follow-up queries used by Kang et al. (2017) can be applied in this proposal. </p>
<p>There are also several related works relevant to the evaluation of satisfaction of using virtual assistants. Kiseleva et al. (2016) divided the structured search dialogue into two groups that were single task search dialogue and multi-task search dialogue. Defined by Kiseleva et al. (2016), the multi-task search dialogue consists of multiple interactions with the intelligent assistant that lead towards one final goal. This proposal focuses on the particular context that selects restaurants, which is the multi-task search dialogue. Therefore, a set of analysing methods that are related to these types of interactions can be employed. Kiseleva et al. (2016) proposed an equation that evaluates the satisfaction of users:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Equation 1: SAT(T1,…,Tm) = h(I(T1,…,Tm)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This evaluation describes a function h that, given a set of interaction signals, would predict user satisfaction (SAT). T1, … , Tm means the tasks in the multi-task search dialogue, while I(T) describes the combination of a set of interaction signals in the tasks (Kiseleva et al., 2016). This method shows 71% to 81% over the baseline in Kiseleva’s (2016) study. Additionally, the follow-up queries with a five-point Likert scale were also employed in Kiseleva’s (2016) research. These two methods can also be used in this proposal due to accuracy and acceptance. Although Jiang et al. (2015) modelled the action patterns and assessed the SAT by proposing the equation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Equation 2: P(v|s,u) = (c(s,u,v)+α·Pml(v|u)+β·Pml(v))/Σvi∈U c(s,u,vi)+α+β</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This equation is too complicated and consists of numerous actions factors. Therefore, only Equation 1 will be used in this proposal. </p>
<h3 id="Quantitative_Study">Quantitative Study</h3><h4 id="Method">Method</h4><h5 id="Participants">Participants</h5><p>A total of 30 participants are projected to be recruited through the Internet, including via emails, social networks and so forth. The participants should be recruited only when they meet two conditions. To be specific, they should not only have a good command of English but also should be familiar with using digital devices. In other words, those who have never used smartphones or cannot speak English will not be recruited. After the experiment, a £10 gift card will be reimbursed as a reward. </p>
<h5 id="Design">Design</h5><p>A factorial experiment will be employed. The primary independent variables are user goal and recommendation structure. User goal is a within-subject factor. It denotes whether the user has a clear goal in mind. For example, “Find a Japanese restaurant around me” will be a vague goal, in contrast to a clear goal like, “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30”. As for the recommendation structure, it is a between-subject factor that refers to three different types of recommendation design. In terms of dependent variables, the five-point Likert scale results, completion time, completion rate, the number of queries and clicks, dwell time and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) rate will be collected during the experiment. These variables measure the error rate, effort, efficiency and throughput. </p>
<h5 id="Material">Material</h5><p>In order to prepare the particular task for this experiment, a virtual assistant prototype will be developed. The prototype should be able to use natural language to interact with users. There also should be a Graphical User Interface (GUI) that displays the list of results whenever users request. The prototype has three different modes explained by flowcharts (a), (b) and (c). The participants from three groups will experience these modes respectively. Flowchart (a) only provides a list of restaurants from which users can select, whereas flowchart (b) and (c) can recommend the user options. The difference between flowchart (b) and (c) is that flowchart (b) provides the recommendation when users are dissatisfied, while flowchart (c) recommends after users have selected one restaurant. In flowchart (b) and flowchart (c), the recommended item should be better than the item the user selects at some aspects (price, distance, etc.).</p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/Flowcharts.png" alt="Figure 1. (a) User flow without recommendations, (b) User flow with recommendations after dissatisfaction, (c) User flow with recommendations after satisfaction" title="Figure 1. (a) User flow without recommendations, (b) User flow with recommendations after dissatisfaction, (c) User flow with recommendations after satisfaction"></p>
<h5 id="Procedure">Procedure</h5><p>There will be a two-minute introduction at the beginning of the experiment. This is to introduce the prototype’s basic functions and to inform participants how to use the multi-task search dialogue. After introducing the virtual assistant, a trial task around selecting restaurants will be conducted before the formal experiment. The trial task is aimed at allowing participants to be familiar with the virtual assistants. During the trial task, participants can choose from numerous example query questions that are presented. These questions range from generally asking for restaurants to asking for a particular distance or price. For example, “Find a Japanese restaurant around me” is a general question, but “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30” contains more detail.</p>
<p>Then the 30 participants will be divided randomly into three groups, each group consisting of 10 people. These three groups will conduct the above three user flows separately. Each participant will conduct the experiment twice with different goals. The first time the participants are assigned to the vague goal that is “Find a Japanese restaurant around me”, the following prompt will be presented.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Imagine that, at this moment, you would like to have dinner in a Japanese restaurant, and that you are about to use a virtual assistant to select one Japanese restaurant, but you do not have very clear criteria for selection. Please use natural language to interact with the virtual assistant, the virtual assistant may give you many choices. If so, select one that suits you most. </em></p>
<p>For the second time, they are assigned a clear goal that is “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30”, and the following prompt will be presented.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Imagine that, at this moment, you are about to use a virtual assistant to select one Japanese restaurant, but this time you have very clear criteria for selection, you would prefer one that is within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30. Please use natural language to interact with the virtual assistant, the virtual assistant may give you many choices, if so, select one that suits you most.
</em></p>
<p>During the experiment, the users’ steps, completion time, number of queries and clicks, dwell time and ASR rate will be collected. After completing the task, all participants will be asked to use the five-point Likert scale to answer the following questions:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    How satisﬁed are you with your experience in this task in general?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    How satisﬁed are you with your experience in each subtask?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    How satisﬁed are you with the final restaurant you selected?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4)    Did you put in a lot of effort to complete the task</em></p>
<p>Regarding the participants in the group with the recommendation, they are required to answer the additional question:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5)    How satisﬁed are you with the recommendation?
</em></p>
<h4 id="Data_Analysis_Plan">Data Analysis Plan</h4><p>The quantitative study deals with the research question about the effects of user goal and recommendation structure on user performance. Because this study is a factorial design, a mixed design ANOVA will be employed to analyse the effects. Regarding the users’ intention, this independent variable has two levels – the vague goal and the clear goal separately. In terms of the effects of the recommendation of virtual assistants, three dependent factors should be paid attention: efforts, error rate and satisfaction. </p>
<p>Initially, the data that involves the severe failure of automatic speech recognition should be excluded. The trials in which users request three times but have not completed the goal should be excluded. This is to decrease the influence of the error on user satisfaction. Secondly, in order to measure the main factors, several measure methods will be utilised. As for the efforts, this factor can be measured by the steps, completion time. Also, the result of five-point Likert scale that corresponds with the question “Did you put in a lot of effort to complete the task?” can measure the efforts. The error can be measured by ASR rate and completion rate. The degree of satisfaction can be measured by the result of five-point Likert scale that involves querying satisfaction. Additionally, Equation 1 that was proposed by Julia Kiseleva (2016) can also measure satisfaction. Therefore, there will be two ways of evaluating satisfaction, the five-point Likert scale and Equation 1. The reason for using two methods is to improve accuracy. What the participants answered may not be consistent with what they really thought, thus the quantified data can reveal such consistency when comparing the two data sets. </p>
<p>Furthermore, a 2x3 repeated measures ANOVA on the participants’ satisfaction value will be run to investigate the effects of the user intention recommendation structure on user satisfaction. By means of comparing the P value with 0.05, the following question can be answered: </p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Whether there is a significant main effect of the user intention on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    Whether there is a significant main effect of the recommendation structure on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    Whether there is a significant interaction effect of user intention × recommendation structure on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>As the effort the user puts in can be one of the attributes of user satisfaction, a similar 2x3 repeated measures ANOVA on the participants’ effort value can be run to investigate the effects of user intention recommendation structure on the user workload. Accordingly, the similar three questions can be answered. Regarding the error rate, the similar practice can be applied.</p>
<p>Additionally, as there are two sets of user satisfaction that are calculated by Equation 1 and 5-point Likert scale, the results of two methods of evaluating efforts and satisfaction should be compared. If they are different to a large extent, the procedure and analysis should require an in-depth investigation, in which way the accuracy can be enhanced.  </p>
<h3 id="Qualitative_Study">Qualitative Study</h3><h4 id="Method-1">Method</h4><h5 id="Participants-1">Participants</h5><p>Ten participants will take part in the study, these participants will be the subset of participants from the quantitative study. Amongst them, five people will be the participants who have interacted with the system that recommended before selection, whereas the other five participants will be the people who have interacted with the system that recommended after selection. </p>
<h5 id="Procedure-1">Procedure</h5><p>The participants will be asked to have an interview after the quantitative experiment. During the quantitative experiment, the researchers should take notes when observing the participants who are about to be interviewed. These notes are aimed at providing insight that allows researchers to ask relevant and valuable questions during the interview. The interview will be semi-structured, this is to ensure a certain degree of freedom and to focus on the research question. The questions can be adjusted based on what the researchers have observed. The research question of the qualitative study is “What are users’ expectations when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants in different intentions (clear goal or vague goal)?” Therefore, around the topic “expectation”, the interview will include the following eight main questions. The questions can also be changed according to the situation:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Did you complete the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    How much effort did you put into the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    How satisfied are you with your final selection?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4)    Did you have any obstacles when doing the task? </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4.1)    If yes, what obstacles did you have during the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5)    How satisfied are you with the recommendation?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5.1)    If yes, do you have any expectations when using it?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5.2).    If no, why are you dissatisfied with it, any suggestions?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>6)    Do you have expectations when you use the virtual assistant?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>7)    Is there any difference between the recommendation and your expectation?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>8)    Do you have any comments about the virtual assistants?</em></p>
<p>The interview will be audio recorded and transcribed later. The researchers are also required to take notes during the interview if the answer is regarded to be important. In terms of interviewees’ answers, if it is insightful, the researcher should ask for an explanation, especially the questions around attitude towards the recommendation. Some participants may select the restaurant that is consistent with the recommendation, some may not. Therefore, the interview questions should be adjusted to discover the deeper reason why they follow the recommendation or not. For example, the user may be dissatisfied with the recommendation because they feel offended or interrupted. The interview time will be limited to 60 minutes. These participants will be reimbursed with a £10 gift card at the end of the interview.</p>
<h4 id="Data_Analysis_Plan-1">Data Analysis Plan</h4><p>The grounded theory will be employed to analyse the data. A three-stage analysis will be employed. Open Coding is the first stage, when the audio will be transcribed. In the transcript, the important small chunks of text should be coded and the keywords and quotes should be marked. More specifically, the words about satisfaction, expectation, obstacles and suggestions should be paid more attention, especially the words that describe the gap between what the users expect and what the virtual assistant actually responds. </p>
<p>The following stage is the Axial Coding, when the correlation amongst those keywords is expected to be found. There will be some relationships between the satisfaction and the obstacles, as the obstacles can account for dissatisfaction. Similarly, the expectation can be related to satisfaction and obstacles, as the satisfaction and obstacles reveal the demerits and improvement of current virtual assistant design. </p>
<p>The final stage is the Selective Coding, where the most frequent keywords or categories should be paid attention to. This is because these frequent concepts have more weight more than other factors. By investigating these frequent factors, a link that can hold all categories together is projected to be found, in which way the common expectation that users have when asking virtual assistants for recommendations will be concluded.</p>
<h3 id="Discussion">Discussion</h3><p>The results of both the quantitative study and the qualitative study will have implications for designing the interaction of virtual assistant. As for the quantitative study, if there is a significant main effect of user intention on user satisfaction, it can be concluded that the designers should apply different strategies to deal with different user goals. Additionally, the results can indicate the suitable recommendation structure in a different context. If there is a significant main effect of the recommendation structure on the user satisfaction, the designer should refer to the recommendation structure that has better user performance: higher satisfaction, lower error rate and effort. Furthermore, the interaction effect of user intention × recommendation structure suggests the suitable recommendation form for virtual assistants when the users have different goals. </p>
<p>One merit of the quantitative study is the factorial design. This design is more efficient than one-factor-at-a-time experiments, and can reveal the interaction effect. Additionally, the within-subject design in the user goal decreases the number of trials, whereas the between-subjects design in recommendation decreases the “carryover effects”, which means that “user participation in one condition may affect performance in other conditions” (Ludlow &amp; Gutierrez, 1976). In terms of the demerits, although the accuracy can be improved by employing two evaluations methods (Equation 1 and five-point Likert scale), such practice takes plenty of time. Additionally, the requirement of the prototype is high, in order to allow users to experience three types of the recommendation structures and the development of the prototype will probably be time-consuming and money-consuming. Additionally, the failure of recognizing the audio can be the confounding variable, so the prototype should be highly capable of recognizing audio. This increases the workload of developing. The reason for not using existing virtual assistants such as Siri and Cortana is the inconvenience of their fixed structure. In other words, employing prototypes have much more flexibility. Although Klemmer et al. (2000) proposed the Wizard of Oz prototyping tool for speech user interface, this proposal suggests using an actual VA. The reason is that employing this prototype can have better ecological validity than using the Wizard of Oz. Therefore, it is necessary to employ the actual virtual assistant. Furthermore, as there are plenty of open-source virtual assistant APIs online, the difficulty of developing can be decreased. </p>
<p>Regarding the qualitative study, the current obstacles to the recommendations of virtual assistants are expected to be found. This can help the designer to decrease the obstacles and improve user satisfaction. Also, user expectation suggests the improvement of virtual assistant design. Based on the gap between what the users expect and what the virtual assistant actually responds, designers can fulfil the user expectations better. The strength of the qualitative study is simplicity. The semi-structured interview does not require a complicated prototype, so it is easy to conduct and can generate a large amount of detail. However, the flexibility of semi-structured interview may decrease reliability. The participants’ answers can be too open to extract keywords. Furthermore, as the study relies on the grounded theory to investigate the interview data, this method helps develop an understanding of user expectations in  a context that is not pre-formed with existing theories (Engward, 2013). However, this method is often difficult to manage, because it requires many more insights and skills. It can be hard to link keywords together in theoretical models at the Selective Coding Stage. Finding a central category that holds everything together is not an easy task. Therefore, the difficulty in analysis and investigation is the weakness of this qualitative study.</p>
<h3 id="Limitations">Limitations</h3><p>The proposed study has a number of limitations. Firstly, the study is limited by the number of participants. This is due to the considerations of the cost of time and compensation. Secondly, the proposal is aimed at researching the recommendation effects for virtual assistants in the context of restaurants and it is unclear whether the same effects work for virtual assistants in other particular contexts. In other words, the external validity may not be high. Such limitation leaves space for future work. Furthermore, as participants from different groups may have different criteria about satisfaction when filling in the five-point Likert scale, this can be a confounding factor when investigating the effects of recommendation structure on user satisfaction. Although this problem can be avoided if the recommendation structure is a within-subject factor, such practice will make the participant repeatedly conduct the experiment six times, which significantly increases the workload of a single participant. As the participant may lose patience or feel tired after a few rounds, the data about user satisfaction will be influenced. Therefore, the current practice probably is a practicable trade-off. On the other hand, part of the participants will be required to take part in both the quantitative study and qualitative study, the experimental time can be more than one and half hour. In this case, participants may feel bored and impatient, leading to the inaccuracy of the data that researcher collected.</p>
<h3 id="References">References</h3><p>Chai, J., Horvath, V., Nicolov, N., Stys, M., Kambhatla, N., Zadrozny, W., &amp; Melville, P. (2002). Natural language assistant: A dialog system for online product recommendation. AI Magazine, 23(2), 63.</p>
<p>Crestani, F., &amp; Du, H. (2006). Written versus spoken queries: A qualitative and quantitative comparative analysis. Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology, 57(7), 881-890.</p>
<p>Engward, H. (2013). Understanding grounded theory. Nursing Standard, 28(7), 37-41.</p>
<p>Jiang, J., Hassan Awadallah, A., Jones, R., Ozertem, U., Zitouni, I., Gurunath Kulkarni, R., &amp; Khan, O. Z. (2015, May). Automatic online evaluation of intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 24th International Conference on World Wide Web (pp. 506-516). International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee.</p>
<p>Kang, J., Condiff, K., Chang, S., Konstan, J. A., Terveen, L., &amp; Harper, F. M. (2017, August). Understanding How People Use Natural Language to Ask for Recommendations. In Proceedings of the Eleventh ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (pp. 229-237). ACM.</p>
<p>Kiseleva, J., Williams, K., Hassan Awadallah, A., Crook, A. C., Zitouni, I., &amp; Anastasakos, T. (2016, July). Predicting user satisfaction with intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 39th International ACM SIGIR conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (pp. 45-54). ACM.</p>
<p>Kiseleva, J., Williams, K., Jiang, J., Hassan Awadallah, A., Crook, A. C., Zitouni, I., &amp; Anastasakos, T. (2016, March). Understanding user satisfaction with intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 2016 ACM on Conference on Human Information Interaction and Retrieval (pp. 121-130). ACM.</p>
<p>Klemmer, S. R., Sinha, A. K., Chen, J., Landay, J. A., Aboobaker, N., &amp; Wang, A. (2000, November). Suede: a Wizard of Oz prototyping tool for speech user interfaces. In Proceedings of the 13th annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (pp. 1-10). ACM.</p>
<p>Lee, S., &amp; Choi, J. (2017). Enhancing user experience with conversational agent for movie recommendation: Effects of self-disclosure and reciprocity. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 103, 95-105.</p>
<p>Ludlow, A., &amp; Gutierrez, R. (2014). Developmental psychology. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan</p>
<p>Matejka, J., Li, W., Grossman, T., &amp; Fitzmaurice, G. (2009, October). CommunityCommands: command recommendations for software applications. In Proceedings of the 22nd annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (pp. 193-202). ACM.</p>
<p>Ozeki, M., Maeda, S., Obata, K., &amp; Nakamura, Y. (2009). Virtual assistant: enhancing content acquisition by eliciting information from humans. Multimedia Tools and Applications, 44(3), 433-448. </p>
<p>Rong, X., Fourney, A., Brewer, R. N., Morris, M. R., &amp; Bennett, P. N. (2017, May). Managing Uncertainty in Time Expressions for Virtual Assistants. In Proceedings of the 2017 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 568-579). ACM.</p>
<p>Smyth, B., McGinty, L., Reilly, J., &amp; McCarthy, K. (2004, September). Compound critiques for conversational recommender systems. In Web Intelligence, 2004. WI 2004. Proceedings. IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on (pp. 145-151). IEEE.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This proposal introduces an experimental method to manage recommendation and explore the use of virtual assistants in the context of a restaurant, and got a distinction mark.<br>]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/HCI/"/>
    
      <category term="Research" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Research/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Digital Story - What is HCI?]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/09/25/hci1/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/09/25/hci1/</id>
    <published>2017-09-24T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:11:10.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a funny digital story explaining what is HCI, have fun guys! <a id="more"></a> (P.S. If you live in China, you might need VPN to watch the following video)</p>
<h5 id="What_is_HCI?">What is HCI?</h5><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QYTTFu1hvVA" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This is a funny digital story explaining what is HCI, have fun guys!]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/HCI/"/>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/HCI/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[新华书店 & 公交车 - 碎片化阅读到一体化体验]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/02/16/portfolio4/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/02/16/portfolio4/</id>
    <published>2017-02-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:10:50.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>新华书店是一家历史悠久的传统书店。随着互联网的发展，人们读书的渠道变得多样化，对于实体书店的认识也发生变化。而这份交互设计作品集，则专注于帮助实体书店在互联网时代重新定位自己的发展方向，以获得用户更多的关注，提高自己的市场份额。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/Bookshop.png" alt="新华书店 &amp; 公交车" title="新华书店 &amp; 公交车"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>新华书店是一家历史悠久的传统书店。随着互联网的发展，人们读书的渠道变得多样化，对于实体书店的认识也发生变化。而这份交互设计作品集，则专注于帮助实体书店在互联网时代重新定位自己的发展方向，以获得用户更多的关注，提高自己的市场份额。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Wecoo - 轻量化小团队协作工具]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/30/portfolio3/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/30/portfolio3/</id>
    <published>2015-10-30T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:08:58.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>wecoo是由我负责管理的一个团队共同完成的一个课程设计，这是一款针对小团体的以信息交流为主的轻量级团队协作移动端应用，wecoo取自we cooperate，中文名是微酷，其针对的目标用户也是兴趣团体、学生组织和社团等小团队。摈弃了文件传输、文件共享等等复杂功能之后，轻量化的wecoo更能给小团体增添活力。<a id="more"></a>在整个产品设计过程中，我是负责产品和团队的管理，参与其中每个流程，负责每个环节的落实，而其中我最主要负责的还是线框图、交互设计、原型设计这几个方面。</p>
<p>wecoo是一款轻量级的团队协作应用，因此在功能上我做了特别多的把控，把文件类的功能全部砍掉，因为这一不适合移动端，二不适用小团体。大的团队一般是以文件为主要协作方式，比如我画了原型给设计师，设计师按原型画设计稿，然后再交付给工程师，这一整个流程都是以文件为主，而学生团体、兴趣团体更多是开会、活动、聚餐等等，这是一种以信息为主的协作方式，因此wecoo针对这类目标用户提出了5种信息流：任务、会议、活动、公告、投票，用这5种信息流来作为团队的协作方式。考虑到wecoo的目标用户分为团队管理者和团队成员，因此wecoo增添了贡献度来辅助管理者进行考勤，并且，wecoo对管理者和成员的呈现方式也略为不同，发起信息流的管理者可以对信息内容进行再编辑，也可以更改成员权限或添加新成员，但成员手中的wecoo是看不到这些icon的，因此更不会对其进行操作，所以这样能做到针对不同用户做到不同层次的简化，使得管理者和成员看到的都是针对他们情况的最简产品。同时，wecoo的团队账单增加了团队账务的透明度，会议和活动的盖楼讨论增添了团队的活力，因此wecoo在很多层面考虑了小团队用户的用户体验。并且，我在wecoo的交互上做了很多提升，比如3D Touch的peek的应用，长按日期快速添加的交互应用，利用系统提醒减少深层级操作的交互应用，这使得用户点击即可查看新成员申请、请假信息、完成任务通知等等，这相当于把深层级的页面提前，从而减少用户的操作流程，即使用户不知道那些深层级的页面，也不需要用户学习，这极大的降低用户的认知负担。</p>
<p>这些交互上的体验一张作品集的图片展现不出来，如果大家想看的话，可以点击<a href="http://ursocute.github.io/wecoo/wecoo2/iphone5s.html" target="_blank" rel="external">交互式原型</a>，来查看上述的交互细节和动效设计，如果还想了解具体的设计流程的话，还可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1pJCHvsf" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>。</p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/wecoo.png" alt="wecoo" title="wecoo"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>wecoo是由我负责管理的一个团队共同完成的一个课程设计，这是一款针对小团体的以信息交流为主的轻量级团队协作移动端应用，wecoo取自we cooperate，中文名是微酷，其针对的目标用户也是兴趣团体、学生组织和社团等小团队。摈弃了文件传输、文件共享等等复杂功能之后，轻量化的wecoo更能给小团体增添活力。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[UI.cn - UI中国iOS版设计初探]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/18/portfolio2/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/18/portfolio2/</id>
    <published>2015-10-17T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:08:12.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>一直很喜欢UI.cn这个网站，有次偶然的机会，我用iPhone的Safari打开UI.cn的时候，发现许多页面并未做成响应式，非常不方便阅读，我再一想，连站酷都有iOS版的，UI中国应该也有iOS版的吧，所以我就跑去App Store里搜，结果什么也没有，这个时候我就萌生了设计UI.cn iOS版的交互原型的想法，做好之后还能放进自己的作品集里。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>我在深入了解了UI中国之后，发现UI中国是以内容为主、浏览学习为主的一个网站，它同时也提供招聘、 找工作、图书推荐、话题社区等服务，但这类服务多为辅，比如话题社区，整页整页都是0回复，因此考虑了这些因素后，我在做UI.cn iOS版的交互时就着重注意了移动端内容阅读的用户体验，把用户偶尔使用的招聘、私信等等功能都放进了层级稍深的抽屉式导航里。而上传作品、上传经验等功能则全部去掉，因为这些功能一不适合移动端，二对用户来说使用频率也不大，因此去掉反而能使应用更加轻便更加易用。总体来说，我个人还蛮喜欢这样的设计的，大家如果感兴趣的话还可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1jGfH46y" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>看一看。</p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/UIcn.png" alt="UI.cn iOS" title="UI.cn iOS"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>一直很喜欢UI.cn这个网站，有次偶然的机会，我用iPhone的Safari打开UI.cn的时候，发现许多页面并未做成响应式，非常不方便阅读，我再一想，连站酷都有iOS版的，UI中国应该也有iOS版的吧，所以我就跑去App Store里搜，结果什么也没有，这个时候我就萌生了设计UI.cn iOS版的交互原型的想法，做好之后还能放进自己的作品集里。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[漫生活 - 轻量级短漫UGC社区]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/06/portfolio1/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/06/portfolio1/</id>
    <published>2015-10-05T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:07:42.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>想当交互设计师，最近就准备了一下自己的交互设计作品集，也不是很确定作品集具体是要做成什么样子，参考了知乎里<a href="http://www.zhihu.com/question/19977449/answer/48279051" target="_blank" rel="external">「交互设计师的简历和作品集应该怎么做才好」</a>这篇的格式，然后按照一般的设计流程完成了角色创建、功能架构、交互设计这几个方面。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>这个产品是我自己构想的，是一个以短篇漫画创作为核心的社区型兼工具型的移动应用，App名叫漫生活，用户只需简单几步就可以创作属于自己的短篇漫画，而用户创作出来的作品叫漫书，相同类型相同话题的漫书放在一起形成漫圈。为了降低用户的学习成本，减少用户的创作流程，创作漫书的过程以模板创作为主，自由创作为辅，创作过程还可以随时保存随时预览，非常方便，完成之后会提供多种分享方式，系统还会根据用户选择的模板提供符合的标签，用户勾选后则发布到相应的漫圈中，与漫友形成互动，构成内容-创作的良性循环。因为这款App是社区型兼工具型的应用，而工具型应用变现能力非常有限，因此我着重突显了应用的社区性，在首页的发现、关注里大面积的推广热门的漫圈和漫书，比如及时推出“叶良辰”的模板和“叶良辰”的漫圈，以高质量的漫书内容和新近的热点话题来激发用户的参与欲与创作欲，从而不断的延长产品的生命，增加App的活跃度。我自己认为这是一款挺有意思的构想，大家有兴趣的话可以看一看，如果还想了解具体的角色创建、功能架构和交互设计，可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1dDjVyY9" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>。</p>
<p><img src="http://pgp8gea1t.bkt.clouddn.com/Comic.png" alt="漫生活" title="漫生活"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>想当交互设计师，最近就准备了一下自己的交互设计作品集，也不是很确定作品集具体是要做成什么样子，参考了知乎里<a href="http://www.zhihu.com/question/19977449/answer/48279051">「交互设计师的简历和作品集应该怎么做才好」</a>这篇的格式，然后按照一般的设计流程完成了角色创建、功能架构、交互设计这几个方面。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
