<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[SHIQI's Blog]]></title>
  
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yoursite.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-18T20:26:42.337Z</updated>
  <id>http://yoursite.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[SHIQI]]></name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[写给聪明人]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2019/01/12/article2/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2019/01/12/article2/</id>
    <published>2019-01-12T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2019-01-18T20:26:42.337Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>从武汉，到北京，再到广州，然后是英国，一路上说难不难，说容易也不容易。我的原生家庭不太能给我提供太多帮助，于是每到一个新地方，一切都得靠自己打拼，很多东西需要自己摸索。现在慢慢静下来，就想写一篇经验性的文章，给后辈里的聪明人看。因为我想，如果你是聪明人，一定能懂得这篇文章里的含义。<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<h3 id="拥有选择权，是人和人最大的区别">拥有选择权，是人和人最大的区别</h3><p>人和人的差距，在于是否有选择权。有了选择权，你才可能选择你自己要的生活方式。很早的时候我爸讲过一个段子，说一个打拼了大半辈子的亿万富翁，退休后居住田园，每天养养花，钓钓鱼，晒晒太阳，觉得特惬意。时间久了，他发现经常身边有个当地渔民每天也和他一起钓鱼，他就很奇怪，说：“你这么年轻，怎么不出去奋斗呢，你要是把这片池子改造成鱼塘，放点鱼苗再撒网捕捞，没几年你就可以收获比钓鱼多得多的财富。“ 当地人问：“那然后呢？” ”然后你就可以像我一样每天养养花，晒晒太阳，钓钓鱼，享受生活了。” ”可是我现在不也是这样吗？“渔民疑惑的回答。</p>
<p>这个段子本想讽刺富人打拼大半辈子，还不如一个乡村渔民。但凡是相信这个段子去讽刺富人的人，一定不会理解富人和渔民的天差万别，他们核心的区别，就在于选择权。渔民没有选择权，他今天钓鱼，明天也得钓鱼，他的人生得靠不停的钓鱼来维持。而富人今天想居住田园，他想住多久就住多久，住腻了，一个飞机就可以飞去巴黎吃个法式大餐，再去伦敦喝个英式下午茶，旅游累了再回归田园，好好晒晒太阳休息一番。</p>
<p>什么能增加你的选择权，无非是钱，权，能力，和资源。我有钱了，我今天想家，立马就能订个明天的机票回国，和家人团聚吃点家里人做的饭。我没有钱，我得提前好几个月买凌晨出发的廉价航班，或者发现春节机票实在太贵，只好打消过年回家的念头，我没有钱，我就没有选择。高考分数高的学生，就能选择他想去的学校，分数太低，只有蓝翔向你招手。本科就积累多个实习经验的学生，以此为资源，没毕业就拿到了多个offer，只用选择想去的公司就行。混过四年毕业一个offer也没拿到的学生，只要有一家公司发了offer他就会感恩戴德，像抓住救命稻草的一样拽住死死不放，把自己原先的选择和坚持置之脑后。</p>
<p>绝大多数抱怨自己曾做出错误决策的人，即使时光倒流让他再来一遍，也一定做不出正确的选择，因为他压根就没有选择。我身边有些人，抱怨父母不送高考失利的自己出国留学，耽误了自己，但这些人很可能连出国留学需要什么材料都不知道，他只会看到我出国留学在英国工作，就觉得留学是一条好路。他不会知道国外学校会看他国内高考分数，会让他参加美国或英国高考，他也不会知道以他的能力可能雅思两三年都考取不了，就算成功去留学了，可能得靠四年代写才能混一个国内甚至都不承认的野鸡大学学历，甚至我有留学的朋友读了好几年书跟我说还在用谷歌翻译写作，这些他都看不到，他不会知道他从一开始就没有选择。</p>
<p>没有筹码，就没有选择权。而这些能增加你筹码构成选择权的东西，不是白白得来的，也不是靠单纯的努力就能获得的，要想拿到属于你的筹码，你需要思考的力量。</p>
<h3 id="聪明的人低看自己，笨的人高看自己">聪明的人低看自己，笨的人高看自己</h3><p>思考的第一步，是知道自己哪儿不足。我和朋友亲戚相处，有觉得我虚伪装的，因为我往往在他们称赞时表现得比较谦虚。这种认知的核心原因，在于对自己和他人实力的误判，这种误判使得能力差的人意识不到自己的不足，而能力强的人看得更远，更意识到自己的不足，反而容易低估自己而表现得谦虚，而这种谦虚在能力差的人眼里，就变成了一种虚伪。</p>
<p>曾经有次亲戚来家里，要我弹钢琴助兴，我就随手弹了一个，我自己觉得弹得挺糟糕，但他们都说好，甚至还有懂音乐的也说好，我当然知道自己差得远了就连忙摆摆手说我还不行。这时候有个亲戚有点气了，说别人都说你好你就好就行了，非这样装干什么。这个时候我才意识到，自己和他人，如果对一个事物的能力不同，那么我们的看法是天差万别的。正因为他不懂音乐，他就不会知道我在弹奏中出的问题，只要没弹中断，那就是好的。相反，正因为我懂，我才知道我哪儿弹快了，哪儿弹重了，哪个音弹错了，哪个地方踏板节奏踩的不对了。</p>
<p>有些人环游世界，觉得这样就增长了见识，但对于没有足够学识的大多数人来说，不过是满世界的厕所打卡。我曾有一次去英国斯旺西旅游，这里有天才诗人Dylan Thomas的纪念馆，斯旺西也因为他而被称为“诗歌海”，然而我并不认识这个诗人，也没读过他的诗，馆藏再漂亮再精致，对我来说不过是几个字母的组合，诗歌手稿里60%的单词我都不认识，参观后在我回忆里留下的只有深深的无知感。那些读过Dylan Thomas诗的人，在这个纪念馆里能感受到多大的震撼，多大的感动，我都无从得知。同样的事物，在不同人眼里是千差万别。认识到自己的无知，是思考的第一步。</p>
<h3 id="会思考的人，行为上才可以偷懒">会思考的人，行为上才可以偷懒</h3><p>和有些人交谈，会发现大多数不曾见识优秀的人，会有一个误区，觉得优秀的人一定付出了巨大的努力。我高中时候发现，很多成绩中下等的学生，往往很努力，并且会把自己成绩提不高怪罪于自己还不够努力。</p>
<p>真正见识过优秀的人才会知道，真正能力强的人往往玩的最狠，高中身边那边每周末去网吧打游戏的都一个个去了南大上交，在家每天奋笔疾书到深夜的却去了江大。这两者本质的区别，就在于是否在思想上勤奋。如果思想勤奋，那么行为上就能偷懒，若是思想懒惰，行为上就得百倍努力。</p>
<p>以这两种人举例，成绩差的人每天学习到凌晨两三点，早上7点起来上学没精打采，上课一半都在打瞌睡，听的新知识也一知半解，于是别人花半小时就能写完的作业，他得花2个小时，一门2小时，5门就10个小时，于是他又写到凌晨3点，开始了新的循环。而在这写作业的过程中，因为他一知半解，所以伴随着翻书，问同学等一系列操作，每次遇到问题他就可以翻书问同学解决。所以等考试的时候，没有书翻，没有人问，一切得靠自己的时候，他就完了。</p>
<p>优秀的人往往11点就睡觉了，第二天精力充沛，上课的时候他是最专注的，尤其是吸收新知识的时候，讲一个公式，他就会去想这个公式怎么来的，可以怎么用，和之前学的可以怎么连上，讲一个单词，他就会聚精会神的记讲解的动作，行为，声音，笑话，以后遇到这个词，所有的环境因素都可以作为提取记忆的线索。因为上课听懂了，课后半小时就能写完一门作业，晚上回家打盘游戏看看电视，早早11点就睡觉了。并且在写作业的过程中，遇到问题他不会马上翻书问同学，他一定会去想自己为什么不会做，是知识点没记牢，那就多看几遍知识点，是公式的应用很巧妙，那他就好好记住这种解题方式，于是他考试的时候，也能靠自己解决大部分问题。</p>
<p>思考上越勤奋，行为上就能越偷懒，否则就得花更多的时间，更多的精力，做重复劳动。只有去思考才可以增加你的筹码，思考是让你拥有选择权的必要非充分条件。</p>
<h3 id="有选择权后，你还需要有选择的能力">有选择权后，你还需要有选择的能力</h3><p>对拥有选择权的人来说，做决策一定是个麻烦事。清华还是北大，我想这个选择还不太难做。但如果你手头有10个offer的时候，去哪儿可能就成了你考虑最多的问题。因为无论去哪儿，都有无数的机会成本在流失。有趣的是，当人没有选择的时候，往往不需要承受丧失机会成本的压力，而选择多了，反而压力大了。</p>
<p>就像做设计遵守设计规范，做选择也需要遵循一些原则，这些原则当然是因人而异，而根据我的经验，首先的一条原则就是，做出能增加不可替代性的选择。</p>
<h3 id="可替代性的单向依赖，是一切灾难的源头">可替代性的单向依赖，是一切灾难的源头</h3><p>许多人抱怨父母的约束，说自己人格独立，不该被管。但这种烦恼的根源其实在于他没有经济独立，经济不能独立，人格也很难独立。这种经济的依赖导致父母成了最大的控制者，单向依赖就是烦恼的根源。父母买房后和父母一起住忍受不了管束，抱怨公司抱怨同事为了房租而不敢辞职，骗钱借钱不惜丧命也要去吸食毒品，丈夫事业腾飞后包二奶而妻子却因经济原因无法离婚，这些都源于依赖。</p>
<p>增加不可替代性，就能增加对方对你的依赖，因此最容易产生价值。假如我是一个餐馆的洗碗工，我洗的再好，再快，一旦餐馆经营不善，没有那么多的人来吃饭，没有那么多的碗洗，我就被淘汰了，又或者我和老板娘有点矛盾，她转眼就能把我辞了，隔天就再招来一个新的洗碗工，这种情况下，我的可替代性很强，如果要选择，我一定不当洗碗工。那当餐馆的财务怎样，假如我是餐馆的财务，我知道怎么处理餐馆所有的收支，税务，流水，这种情况下我和老板娘就算有点矛盾，她可能也因为我一定程度的不可或缺而不去炒我，因为招聘一个新的财务，肯定得花不少的时间成本来熟悉业务，甚至新财务可能不知怎么合理避税，则会让餐馆损失更多。但这也不是绝对的，万一老板娘真打心底里瞧不起我，非要炒了我而给她远房亲戚的二舅的侄女一个当财务的机会，也不是不可能，那我还是可被替代。但如果我是餐馆的食材供应商呢，假如这个餐馆一直以食材新鲜优质而广受好评，而我是餐馆主要的食材供应商，一旦我不同意供应了，餐馆可不会像炒一个洗碗工一样，那么容易就马上找一个新的优质渠道，于是老板娘只会拍拍我笑着说：”大哥你开啥玩笑呢，是我们哪儿没做好吗，都可以商量可以谈的，觉得哪儿不好我们改，别动不动就说不供应了，大哥你说是吧。“</p>
<p>看清楚这个行业，这个领域中最不可替代的地方，努力的去占据这个位置，就能减少依赖，增加适应。如果一个选择能帮助接近行业最不可替代的核心节点，那么就做这个选择，让自己变成这个核心节点。如果你的能力是创造价值，那么就去私企行业创造出价值，变成不可替代的价值源泉。如果你的能力是八面玲珑情商高的多面手，那么就去产能过剩的国企行业，因为越清闲的地方越不需要创造价值，就越会产生办公室政治，而你的多面手能力就是最不可替代的。人是社会的动物，完全不依赖是不可能的，我们每个人都一定程度的依赖于他人，依赖于社会，但即使是这样，我们也要尽量做到双向依赖，这样两方势力才会不断纠缠，从而谁也没法给谁施压，局势才会更加稳定。俄罗斯和美国在经济上纠缠较少，美国说制裁就能制裁，而中国和美国经济相互纠缠，硬生生扯开只会让两方都受伤，于是即使是灯塔国也得三思而后行，不敢随便的轻举妄动。减少单向依赖能增加稳定性，增加不可替代性能增加适应性。</p>
<p>可以说，在做留英还是回国的选择时，不可替代性也是指导我做决策的原则之一。如果我在英国工作太久，我将会很大程度依赖于英国的公司，一旦公司裁掉我，我必须要在1个月内找到新工作，否则我的签证就会失效，这相当于是不可能的任务，这种极大的依赖可不是什么好事。其次，英语能力和文化因素也让我很难在英国职场升职加薪，也就是说以我的能力很难在英国职场上变成那个不可替代的节点，那么相比之下，还不如回国寻找国内领域的不可替代节点。</p>
<h3 id="顺应时代，让可复用的经验变成跳板">顺应时代，让可复用的经验变成跳板</h3><p>老一辈的人由于时代的局限性，往往认为国企，公务员是最稳定的工作，千方百计找关系也要让子女去一个月薪两三千的事业单位，我身边这样的不要太多。然而，这种稳定性其实不一定高，因为某些事业单位让每个员工过多的依赖于单位，而某些岗位又涉及长期的重复劳动，而一旦有一点变动，这个人被放到市场上就失去了所有的竞争力，因为这份重复劳动的经验无法在市场上被复用。</p>
<p>我身边有些长辈找关系让子女去了煤炭发电厂，认为这样很稳定，但传统的电厂却已是夕阳产业，日薄西山，也许10年，20年还可以投入使用，但30年，40年呢，这样的夕阳产业必然很大程度的受到新能源发电的冲击，一旦发生产业转型，架构调整，不幸被裁员，这份电厂扳手使用的工作经验无法在市场上被复用，于是只能被时代淘汰，过多的依赖于夕阳产业的单位，是一枚极其不稳定的定时炸弹。相比之下，一些在市场上选择了适应性更强的工作的人，即使被裁员，这些经验也可以变成跳板，让他跳去更高更广的舞台。只有理解了政治经济的大环境，和时代前进的方向，才能在未来很长的时间维度上去做决策，这就是为什么有些女生在择偶时只看到眼下的房和车，而有些女生却知道真正长时间相处的话，三观、性格、上进、共同努力有多么的重要。</p>
<p>这和我在英国工作的问题也很类似，英国的公司文化，工作方式和国内都有很大的不同，我回国后这些英国工作的经验很多无法复用，那么国内公司很可能不倾向录用我，我都能想象国内的面试官会怎么问我，我们这都用敏捷开发的工作流程，你在英国是这样吗，我说不我们不用，面试官又问，那我们这都是产品来完成PRD交代迭代细节，你们那是吗，我们说不我们都不写PRD直接上原型的。那这种情况国内面试官会倾向于录用一个工作方式完全不同的英国工作的人，还是一个适应国内工作流程的人呢？</p>
<p>不可替代性和依赖性的原则，更多适用于为别人工作的选择，而对于自己当老板的人来说，可能你还需要懂一点经济学。</p>
<h3 id="利用好边际效应递减的原理">利用好边际效应递减的原理</h3><p>无论是自己当老板，还是追求财务自由，财富自由，核心的关键点在于找到边际效应递减的节点。用我表哥来举例，他是一个教街舞的机构的老板，在这种情况下，他假如自己来教，如果每天教6个小时，头一个小时和最后一个小时是完全不一样的，这种情况是边际效应递增的，因为当教最后一个小时的时候，人已经非常疲惫了，这个时候需要克服疲惫打起精神再完全最后一个小时的教学，这可比头一个小时累多了，这样的商业模式就是成本递增的。</p>
<p>但如果他招其他人来帮他教呢，情况就不一样了，这个时候多教一个人，多教一个小时，对于老板都没有太多的成本增加。而如果此时招人的工资和教学的收入能平衡的话，这就是边际效应递减的关键节点了，因为此刻只要多教一个学生，付给街舞老师的工资不会因为这个学生而有太多增加，电费和场地费也不会因为多了一个学生而有太多增加，那么这种情况下学生越多，就能用越少的成本换取越多的利润。那么如果达到了这样的节点，关键就在于招生的渠道，那么如何获取优质渠道，找到稳定渠道，就是后话了。</p>
<p>只有找到自己的边际效应递减的节点，才可以减少自己的重复劳动，更进一步实现财务和财富的自由。</p>
<h3 id="人脉的有效与否在于你自己有没有用">人脉的有效与否在于你自己有没有用</h3><p>很多长辈都很看重人脉的作用，这有时代局限性的因素。在过去的年代，很多人办事，找工作，升职，分房子，都是上面的人一句话的事。这种情况下，人脉和情商就显得尤为重要。但时代的发展让这些越来越不现实，而如果在现在的时代还以这样的眼光看待人脉，往往得不到有效的人脉。</p>
<p>人脉的有效与否其实在于自己的资源是否有利益交换的资本。人脉的本质是利益的交换，如果自己没有价值，那么人脉的桥梁永远是单向，就像单向的依赖一样，无法稳固的维持下去。就好比一个成绩差的学生为了抄作业，去勾搭成绩好的学生，也许成绩好的学生可以借一两次，但借多了，成绩差的又没有什么能提供的，这种关系一定无法长久的维持。假如你15年前和马云吃了餐饭，你也不可能因为这点打个电话就让马云给安排个工作，因为双方在资源配置上已经完全不对等了。双向依赖是人脉的基本，当没有让人依赖的资本的时候，所有的人脉都是无效的，这就是为什么一些校园里叱咤风云的学生会主席，在毕业各分东西的时候，才发现自己其实并没有真正可以调用的人脉资源。</p>
<p>当然也有一些人会反驳我，我有些亲戚朋友就非常看重人脉，认为学习不如人脉重要，我想他可能是看到了一些拥有人脉的人更容易找到工作或升职加薪，但即使是这样，人脉的基础仍然是资源的交换，某些投行在招聘的时候更愿意招有关系的人，你觉得别人看到的是关系，其实别人看到的是对方父母背后的资源，更有效的信息渠道，更庞大的资源网络，这就是用来交换的资本。与其想着拥有人脉，不如先让自己拥有资源。</p>
<h3 id="理解时代的局限性">理解时代的局限性</h3><p>很多人抱怨父母和老一辈的人和自己的观念不同，其实长辈的观念不是错的，只是不适应这个时代了，曾适用于他们时代的法则在这个时代不生效了，这种时代局限性是可以理解的。就好像我的亲戚都劝我留在英国，他们认为在英国工作了再回国一定吃香，其实这没有错，不过是在30年前没错，在如今这个时代的我的行业里已经不是这样的了。我拿到国内offer和HR谈薪资的时候，想用国外的offer作筹码增加点薪水，说我在英国可以拿2倍多的钱了，能不能再加一点，结果HR说我们这很多国外工作回来的，都是降薪了的，国内和国外肯定不能比，没有可比性，不能这样比。HR就这样一句话就把我的提议否决了，亲戚有时代局限性是可以理解的，但我如果自己也被过去的时代局限，以为只要在英国工作了，回国就吃香了，那么最后自讨苦吃的只会是我自己。</p>
<p>爱因斯坦在他的时代不相信量子力学，说上帝不掷骰子，结果大错特错。牛顿潜心研究神学判断人类历史只有200年，这些都是时代局限性导致的，我们可以保持一份理解，只不过我们自己不能被时代局限，尤其是被过去的时代所局限。在现在这个时代，如果长辈还费尽心思找关系想让你去某个夕阳产业的国企从基层做起，那么你自己应该有自己的认知，要知道怎样才能增加自己的不可替代性，怎样增加适应性，什么才是真的稳定。</p>
<p>这个时代，拥抱变化的适应性才是最大的稳定。有不少的朋友和我说，他不想奋斗，就想找一份不需要学习可以一直做下去的工作，就轻松的过日子。这样的生活方式当然是好的，然而抱着这样想法的人，往往不能过这样轻松的日子。去煤炭电厂的人也是这么想的，每天用扳手看着仪表，不用怎么学习就可以一直做下去，而这样的夕阳产业日薄西山被新能源替代的时候，这样的日子就可以随时到头，而只有真正具备适应性的人，才能真的过轻松的日子，你的思维方式决定了你会过怎样的生活。</p>
<h3 id="平静的看待各种主义">平静的看待各种主义</h3><p>我们这个时代有很多主义，消费主义，大男子主义，女权主义，民族主义，要我说，我认为要平静的去看待这些主义，而不要陷入其中，一旦陷入其中，这份主义很可能遮蔽你的视野，把你的格局完全困在其中，无法逃脱。就拿民族主义来说，陷入民族主义情绪，就无法真正理性的去看待问题，相反会变得情绪化，产生戾气。比如有朋友，在我一谈到国家存在的问题时，就会反驳说：“别人国家难道就没有吗，为什么你就只注意到不好的地方，别人就都是好的吗？”这样的论调一提出，就没法真正去探讨原本存在的问题了。以种族主义举例， 我曾在知乎微博看过太多种族歧视的案例，有说在英国看到小孩和青少年辱华的，有说旅游学习都看不到，一到工作的时候就遇到了明显区别对待，有说中国人在国外是二等公民的，类似的论调和举例数不胜数，看到这些我同样会义愤填膺，充满戾气。不过我马上就平静了下来，因为我问了自己一句，“我遇到过吗？”答案是几乎没有，我在英国两年几乎没有遇到过类似的歧视，仅仅的一次还来源于一个没给钱所以愤愤不平的流浪汉，即使我在这边工作了，所有的同事也是相当的友好和礼貌，所以我发现，一旦我陷了进去，我的情绪就被控制了，我的格局就被缩小了，于是我反而看不到我真实的生活了。</p>
<p>又好比女权主义，过多陷入女权主义，会倾向于将一切问题归结于男权社会，而忽略了男女不平等只是更大的阶级矛盾中的一部分。比如我有朋友就认为婚姻是对女性的剥削，因为婚姻的最初基础是女性成为某个男性的所有物，但这样的论调不仅让人产生戾气，还让人忽视现实问题。也许最初的婚姻确是如此，但如今早已不可同日而语，婚姻的基础在于互相所有，互相放弃一部分自由而选择在一起，如果如今的婚姻的基础仍是女性成为某个男性的所有物的话，男性的出轨和包养也会被接受，因为妻子仅仅是其中的所有物，但我们都知道，婚姻的基础并不在此。男性和女性相处，除了相互所有，还要共同成长。只有两个人都保持相同的成长速度，共同进步，才能棋逢对手，长久的相处。一旦成长速度差不一样，一方很容易看得更多更远，走入了新的世界，而另一个人没能跟上，观念和价值产生冲突，导致最终关系破裂。</p>
<p>对于消费主义，如果绝对理性的看待，会发现消费主义让人相信我消费我生活就更好的理念，生活不顺利了消费让自己开心，升职加薪去消费犒劳自己让自己开心，消费成了生活享乐的宗旨和方式，是这个时代新的宗教，大家以为把带格纹（Burberry）的衣服穿身上就是自信就是好的，把两个G（GUCCI）露在外面就是成功的优秀的，但这些本质上不过是符号和棉质面料而已，但我们却相信穿上印了这个符号的棉质面料我就能变得更好更成功的，这无非是一种新宗教。消费主义还有由奢入俭难的依赖性，穿了Burberry，就再也不穿Jack Wills，穿了联名鞋，就再也不买普通鞋，用了Prada包就再也背不回原来的双肩包，消费一旦发生变成习惯，就会一定程度成瘾，除非有外界环境干扰，这种消费等级不会下降。一开始只打算买一件Burberry衬衣，但潜移默化的降不下去，反而新增了新的需求，因为需要和衬衣搭配的衣服鞋，于是就又买了Burberry风衣帽子鞋甚至伞，这种消费主义的渗透，让陷入其中的人看不清自己真正想要的生活。</p>
<p>你一定以为我要讽刺消费主义了，其实正好相反。绝对理性的分析会是批判，但人是不会永远理性的，我们总会有感性的一面。如果我们存了几个月的钱，去买一件我们想要很久的衣服，想要很久的包，那一刻我们是幸福的，是喜悦的，穿出去也是自信的，甚至这是我们老了也会记得的事情，会和我们的后代说，我年轻的时候可追潮流了，存了好几个月的钱就为了买那件衣服，买了还天天穿，别提多高兴了。我们的人生不就是由这么一个个情绪体验构成的吗，所以，一边克制，一边及时行乐吧。</p>
<h3 id="每一片雪花都是无辜的">每一片雪花都是无辜的</h3><p>成长最大的标志是平静，平静的去接受变化，接受自己，也接受他人。有时候我们需要接受自己的平凡平庸，有时候我们需要理解长辈因时代局限性而产生的传统观念，有时候我们需要接受他人因个人痛苦的经历而产生的戾气与愤怒，有时候我们需要接受作为个人在这个庞大的社会机器前的无力与无助。有一句话说“雪崩时，没有一片雪花是无辜的”，我很讨厌这句话。雪崩的时候，每一片雪花都被另一片雪花推着前进，每一片雪花都没有能力自己来选择自己前进的方向，只能被社会，时代逼着前进，作为个人雪花的我们，很多时候是无力的，相比指责每一片雪花，我认为平静的接受这种无力，是一种真正的智慧，因为这种平静会给你力量，会让你不被无力所绑住，不被各种主义所限制。每个人都被其成长环境，文化，国家，时代所局限，我们都是这一片片雪花，左右不了前进的方向，但如果平静的去看待，也许你会发现一个格局更大的自己。</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>从武汉，到北京，再到广州，然后是英国，一路上说难不难，说容易也不容易。我的原生家庭不太能给我提供太多帮助，于是每到一个新地方，一切都得靠自己打拼，很多东西需要自己摸索。现在慢慢静下来，就想写一篇经验性的文章，给后辈里的聪明人看。因为我想，如果你是聪明人，一定能懂得这篇文章里的含义。<br>]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Article" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/Article/"/>
    
      <category term="Article" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Article/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[伦敦，冬天，碎念]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2018/11/16/article1/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2018/11/16/article1/</id>
    <published>2018-11-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-19T21:55:33.357Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>这是让人感到冰冷的房间<br>无法停止上升的，只有体温<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>高烧的温度提高了代谢<br>思考的速度反而加快了<br>他想到高考，留学，工作<br>像是一个漫长的镜头<br>再多的场面，再多的演员<br>能让人记住的总是那些哽在喉头的刺</p>
<h3 id="“你们在我们眼里，就是一群屌丝”">“你们在我们眼里，就是一群屌丝”</h3><p>“什么？”少年嘴角动了一下，这句“什么”差点连自己都没听到<br>“我说，”她顿了顿，理直气壮地讲道：“你们就是一群屌丝。”<br>坐在少年对面的，是一个高中时的女性好友<br>几年没见了，临近大学毕业<br>他们约在武汉天地<br>“你呀，别总和你们那一波玩，你们在我们眼里就是一堆屌丝。”她一边吃着少年给烤好的烤肉，一边点评着他的高中好友，每一个男生都没放过。<br>“那个Z，在我们眼里就一屌丝，没什么别的。那个X是很会讲道理，我跟你说，那是因为他以为这样助人为乐就可以追到妹子才这么做的，还有那个H，总是说些猥琐的东西，很不尊重女生好嘛。C倒是不错，有过女朋友，不过老是装苦情，B没啥别的，完全不懂女生，一点也不会哄人。”<br>但少年眼里，他们似乎是完全不一样的人<br>Z家境普通，却一直在努力奋斗。X向往爱情，愿意去追逐心愿。H说的笑话偶尔会带颜色，但从来都是贬损男生，不曾针对女生。C有点文艺，朋友圈像诗。B直博直硕，导师争抢<br>回家路上，女生虽然比少年住得远，但少年还是让司机先送她到家，再到自己家<br>在车上女生把“你们就是一群屌丝”又重复了一遍<br>他窘迫到不敢看司机<br>却还是付了电影钱，饭钱，还有车钱<br>少年更在意的是，她变了<br>回家，拉黑了</p>
<p>拉黑后，少年突然想到<br>其实女生有夸赞他<br>她说，“像你还是不错的，还能和女生说几句话，吃个饭。”<br>这样的夸赞，是要做阅读理解的<br>原来能和女生说话吃饭，是一种宠幸和荣耀<br>其实少年一直都相信异性间的友谊<br>甚至相比男生，他更喜欢和女生玩<br>但他从拉黑的女生这里，感到了微妙的不平等<br>他想起曾经他和表亲的朋友说，自己和某些异性只是朋友<br>当时被嘲讽，那些说只是朋友的都有目的<br>他不明白<br>他幻想到未来的某一天，一个叫“奇葩说”的节目，会探讨起男女生吵架谁先道歉的问题<br>让男生先道歉？<br>是直男在歧视女性没有讲道理的能力。<br>让女生先道歉？<br>是直男癌</p>
<h3 id="“你会不会把我杀了啊？”">“你会不会把我杀了啊？”</h3><p>少年没懂<br>“不是很多这种新闻吗，把人拐到一个地方然后杀掉”<br>跟少年对话的，是一起住学生宿舍的新学生a<br>她用微信发给他看自己的画，连续70张<br>她下午3点把少年叫起来吃她做的牛排，没有任何预兆<br>她早上7点一个电话把少年吵醒，让他去开大门<br>她凌晨2点跑来敲门，送东西<br>她打电话实在太过频繁，<br>少年跟她说有事可以微信，不用每次都打电话<br>a就突然哭了，说你不喜欢接我电话<br>最糟糕的追求，莫过于<br>得失心，和不会表达</p>
<p>少年有女朋友，a没有停下<br>让a停下的是一通话，a听到了少年和女朋友通话<br>按a的话说，她从来没听到少年这么温柔的时候<br>第二天，a宣布她有男朋友了<br>a和国内一个追她很久的学弟在一起了<br>伦敦和北京，异地<br>但a还是总给少年打电话问续签<br>一次少年讲了个大概，a后来发现其中一个环节要盖章，少年没提到<br>a说少年有心机，说自己很单纯，世界很复杂，一切都是利益。a说大家不愿意和她玩，因为得不到利益<br>“单纯”，少年突然想到，a的妈妈也提到过，a来宿舍的那天她妈也来了，看到少年也问东问西，首先问的是你哪儿人<br>少年说武汉，不知怎么a妈露出了一丝失望的表情，后来a提到，她妈要她找北京当地的。<br>不过a妈很快就换上了诚恳的表情<br>“我家孩子很单纯，没出过什么远门，希望还多关照”</p>
<p>a没有放弃找男朋友<br>应该说，没有放弃再找男朋友<br>一次她哭着跑来找少年诉苦，说被一个男生拉黑了<br>她喜欢上了新的男生，同样的追求方式<br>男生不喜欢她，爱答不理<br>一气之下，a拉黑了男生，又气不过加了回来<br>和男生说<br>“对不起我不小心把你拉黑了”<br>于是。男生就真的把她拉黑了</p>
<p>a一直向少年哭诉<br>她不停地说，她太笨了，那个男生还挺帅的，就这样没了<br>“那你男朋友呢，他在国内，你不觉得这样骑驴找马对他有点不公平吗”<br>a没说话了好一会<br>“我男朋友说。“<br>a解释道，”我有喜欢的就可以去追的”<br>只是这样心态是卑微是洒脱<br>谁是驴谁是马，我们都不得而知</p>
<h3 id="“我总不能找个bitch吧”">“我总不能找个bitch吧”</h3><p>对面的女生怨恨地说到，声音很大，充满仇视，吓了在桌的外国室友一跳<br>少年坐在对面，很害怕，因为她仇视的正是男性<br>“毕业的时候，那些男生都找到工作了，别人要翻译，得去非洲，我们女生怎么去啊”<br>“我读博士毕业都30岁了，你们男生又非要找20岁的，凭什么，我也要找20岁的”<br>少年劝她工作没那么难找，很多公司不那么挑专业，可她还是执意读博<br>“我们女生又不像男生那样奋斗，我们女生呢，想法就很简单，就想找个轻松的工作，比如读博当老师，时间多也轻松”<br>女生不知道，她的前后逻辑是矛盾的<br>不是所有30岁男生，都能娶妙龄少女<br>得有资本，要么事业有成，要么英俊帅气<br>少说，是奋斗10年才能拥有的资本<br>而读博出来的她，30岁，文学博士，没有妙龄少女的容颜，也没有稳步上升的事业<br>她想要翻译的工作，却不愿意去非洲<br>她想要时间多轻松的工作，不想像男生一样辛苦的奋斗<br>她想向下兼容找年轻对象，却不想先奋斗10年去拥有向下兼容的资本<br>不知道世上有没有这样的好事</p>
<p>“你不请我一杯的？”<br>c埋怨地问道<br>不知道为什么，c总是让少年感觉不舒服<br>主动请完一杯又马上要求回请<br>c喜欢一个女生，但车票却是少年和女生坐一起<br>c一屁股坐下，说座位给我吧，好像理所应当<br>他偶尔来找少年，在少年有国内offer时，在少年可以留英工作时<br>后来少年知道，有种不舒服叫<br>目的性太强</p>
<h3 id="少年，第一次参加年会">少年，第一次参加年会</h3><p>一群人中间，站着一个胖子。<br>周围的人举着杯子，像流水线上加工好的一批批产品<br>轮流面带笑容迎上去<br>他们是最后一批产品中的一个，因为老王说<br>让业绩好的产品批次先去<br>“老王啊，老，王。”胖子说，“我看你就叫老王吧”<br>这个“吧”拖的特别长<br>会场上的产品们都大笑了起来<br>其中有个产品低着头作揖，“王八好，感谢老大赐名”<br>“我看你这个新名字挺好的。”不仅胖子说，旁边的其他批产品也笑着说。<br>“老大，我们去年没做成什么事，真的对不起，我先走一个”<br>老王拿着一满杯白酒，一饮而尽。连同这批次的其他产品，包括少年。<br>“诶诶，你喝这么多不行的。”胖子好心。<br>虽然他可能知道，上去之前，这批产品的杯子里都兑了水。<br>包括少年。</p>
<p>老王走了，小z来了<br>小z是少年的新leader<br>他劝少年大四别回学校了，和辅导员打个招呼，考试找学弟代考，少年没说话<br>少年工作能力不错，给小z省了不少事<br>有一天小z找到他，拉到会议室。<br>“你啊，工作效率蛮高，挺好，每天9点就下班了。但我们做产品的，开发没走，我们也得在着陪着，你看b，还有x，哪个不是呆在12点1点的。”<br>这之后，每天11点前，少年都没回家<br>“这周六能来吗”<br>少年知道，小z不是真的在询问<br>少年想出国，本来提前3天说离职就行，他提前了1个月说，给团队时间招人<br>不相信，这是小z听了的第一反应，好像到手的鸭子飞了<br>“不，不是。”小z慌了<br>“你看，互联网这一行哪有出国的，你在我这里呆两年当骨干，出去不是抢着要？”<br>看不为所动，小z继续想办法，“你说自费还是奖学金，你要自费但话未免有点太奢侈了，你可以工作几年再去，我身边挺多同事是这样的。”<br>看还是没有动摇，小z有点恼羞成怒。<br>“你们这些人是不是都有些什么，名校情结啊，非要去读”<br>小z确实不懂，毕竟他是个三本出身，靠会站队走到现在。少年有点怀念老王，北邮，90后，每次都站在他的立场考虑。<br>小z使出了大杀招，应该说，是他认为的大杀招<br>“你想20岁就买车吗”小z问<br>“我当时很早就跟着老李干，我20岁有天晚上等车，觉得很煎熬，第二天就提了一辆车，如果你留下来，你也可以”<br>那天下班，12点，小z第一次提出开车送少年回家<br>奔驰，一股锈味<br>离职前，小z留了一句话<br>“有钱人家孩子是不一样啊”<br>后来少年又去了广州工作，离职的时候leader只有一句话<br>但少年记很深<br>“想回来，找我”</p>
<h3 id="高考那年，少年在聚会上。">高考那年，少年在聚会上。</h3><p>好像他是主角，好像他不是。<br>他不知道说些什么，当身边的人向他举着杯子时。<br>“建筑专业才好”“考上南大才叫厉害”“西安交大才能进我们单位”<br>人是种奇妙的生物，能坦然接受思聪，却对身边的人的优秀，心存芥蒂。<br>少年惭愧，少年低头。<br>他还不懂在场的情绪，是妒忌。</p>
<p>一个人拍了拍少年肩膀，在聚会几年后。<br>这个人比较高，伸出的手格外亲近。<br>他是少年的归国表亲，滔滔不绝的讲着国外的故事。<br>少年很是新奇，看着他，仿佛面对着一个新的世界。<br>正巧，路过了少年的高中学校，表亲指着大楼问，“你们当时就在这儿上课吗。”<br>少年解释说不，那栋是为分校准备的。<br>“那分校本校有什么区别呢？”<br>“分校主要是给分数不高，但是毕竟家里有背景的人上的，需要交钱才能上。本校就难了，分数高，差一分都进不了。有人说是用本校出成绩，分校创收。”<br>“那你当时还去什么本校”表亲突然一句让人吃了一惊。“还不如去分校，随便跟个背景好的搞好关系，到时候工作出路什么都不愁，还学什么习。”<br>与其说是不懂，更多的是惊讶，读书无用论居然会从留学表亲口里说出。<br>表亲不会知道，就这一句将会彻底疏远和少年的关系。<br>因为这是少年第一次感受到的，价值观的冲撞。<br>现场，沉默。</p>
<p>“下周有没有空，我请你吃饭”<br>亲戚特别诚恳，拉着少年的手<br>很久以后少年回国了，带着留英资格和学历<br>人是一种奇妙的生物，当身边的人比他好一点的时候<br>他会羡妒<br>当好很多的时候，他会巴结<br>“我跟你说，你就别回国了，在英国干几年，回国抢着要”<br>虽然少年说了几遍不适应英国的饮食和生活，但亲戚似乎并不顾这些<br>一群人围着少年，恭维祝福<br>他们不知道，少年此时很懊恼<br>他满脑子都是同学的聚会，他翘掉了今晚和同学的剧本杀<br>来应付热心的亲戚</p>
<h3 id="“其实毕业也不用马上工作，gap一年也挺好的”">“其实毕业也不用马上工作，gap一年也挺好的”</h3><p>少年其实很羡慕，那些可以gap的人<br>身边许多人都选择了gap<br>但少年不可以<br>这个世界，有两个东西重要<br>有能力选择，和选择的能力<br>少年没有选择<br>有些人有选择，去gap<br>有些人相信了诗与远方，也gap<br>回国发现工作难找，大厂难进<br>不是应届生身份，社招又没工作经验<br>机会成本，不是每个人都能填补<br>有背景的人有父母填补<br>有钱的人有资本填补<br>那，我们呢</p>
<p>人都是贪婪的动物<br>见过了好的，就接受不了差的<br>有长辈来家做客过<br>聊到“大学里有很多城市的孩子相比农村的，更努力”<br>长辈说，“因为农村家里有地，有退路”<br>但，那是退路吗？<br>曾经是退路，现在却不是了。<br>对见到城市生活的孩子来说<br>那是深渊。<br>多少人在北上广打拼而不愿回家<br>多少人买起奢侈品再不回归简单<br>多少人拼命移民只为了一个身份<br>见过好的，差的就再也变不回退路<br>变成了深渊</p>
<p>英国工作，氛围轻松<br>节奏慢，按时上下班，一个月年假<br>英国呆越久，就越接受不了<br>加班，奋斗，压榨<br>曾经拥有的一些东西<br>就变成了深渊<br>放不下国内的生活和人际<br>丢不下国外的轻松和秩序<br>当有了能力选择<br>选择反而变成割舍<br>放弃校招offer<br>还是放弃英国工作永居<br>人都是贪婪的动物<br>一方面拿着英国工签工作<br>一方面推迟校招offer入职时间<br>若赶在失效前回国入职<br>就有了一年国外工作经验<br>外加一个校招offer<br>亦或是用国外工作的一年做缓冲区<br>就给自己充分的时间去做最后的决定<br>贪婪的选择</p>
<h3 id="伦敦，冬天">伦敦，冬天</h3><p>一个人国外生病<br>感受只有自己知道<br>朋友笑说，国外有自由的空气<br>少年说，那也是自由和孤独的空气<br>一个人走走逛逛，再好<br>也会有某刻急切想要分享的冲动<br>看过的景，听过的曲<br>不缺假日<br>但假日里，只有假装过节日的人<br>也许病好，就醒了。</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>这是让人感到冰冷的房间<br>无法停止上升的，只有体温]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="Article" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/Article/"/>
    
      <category term="Article" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Article/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[PlantPeace - A Peaceful Living Space]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2018/01/16/portfolio6/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2018/01/16/portfolio6/</id>
    <published>2018-01-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:31:16.289Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes a noise management system that helps students (noise suffers and noisemakers) who lives in student accommodation to deal with noise issues. Welcome to any comments : )<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/hlqcQy0.jpg" alt="PlantPeace" title="PlantPeace"></p>
<p>There is also an introduction video about PlantPeace (P.S. If you live in China, you might need VPN to watch the following video)</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mF0U2w5V3f8" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>The porfolio got the distinction mark, here is the individual feedback from <a href="https://uclic.ucl.ac.uk/people/nicolai-marquardt" target="_blank" rel="external">Nicolai Marquardt</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Excellent quality of presented portfolio; great to see variety of design methods. Very high quality portfolio design, with a clear structure and layout. Very refined sketches and visual mockups. Great to see sampling of a larger design space (the sketches on page 4 were great, but some of them a bit difficult to see). Excellent wireframes! You could possibly improve some of the descriptions of your designs, by better explaining the function of a design, what is shown and how it works (e.g., the storyboard or wireframe on page 4, or the wireframes on page 5). It would be good to more explicitly describe the criteria for selecting designs and/or methods.”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Finally, if you want to know more about the PlantPeace Project, you can click here and find more details in the <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1atqw-PG3zBPLzxM2hubm61ITZzChPCcl/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="external">report</a>.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes a noise management system that helps students (noise suffers and noisemakers) who lives in student accommodation to deal with noise issues. Welcome to any comments : )]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[DeeperTrip - A Deeper Insight into Scenic Spot]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2018/01/15/portfolio5/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2018/01/15/portfolio5/</id>
    <published>2018-01-15T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:30:50.024Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes an AR product that helps users get a deeper insight of the culture and history of scenic spots. Welcome to any comments : )<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/Idutl45.png" alt="DeeperTrip" title="DeeperTrip"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This Ixd portfolio describes an AR product that helps users get a deeper insight of the culture and history of scenic spots. Welcome to any comments : )]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Exploring the Use of Virtual Assistants in a Restaurant]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/12/25/hci2/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/12/25/hci2/</id>
    <published>2017-12-25T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:28:16.575Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This proposal introduces an experimental method to manage recommendation and explore the use of virtual assistants in the context of a restaurant, and got a distinction mark.<br><a id="more"></a></p>
<h3 id="Introduction">Introduction</h3><p>“Hey Siri, find me a restaurant.” “OK, here is what I found,” said Siri, with a search engine results page presented. This conversation is a common scene for those who use virtual assistants (VA) in their daily lives. Defined as “an artificial agent that simulates a human assistant and prompts users to provide feedback by asking questions” (Ozeki, Maeda, Obata &amp; Nakamura, 2009), VAs are expected to become the next generation of Human Computer Interaction (HCI). Vying to lead this new generation of HCI, numerous enterprises are developing virtual assistants, such as Google Now, Amazon’s Alexa, Apple’s Siri and Facebook M. These virtual assistants innovate HCI as dialogue-style interactions, and allow users to access numerous services, such as launching apps, making phone calls, reading messages, playing music and others (Lee &amp; Choi, 2017; Rong, Fourney, Brewer, Morris &amp; Bennett, 2017).</p>
<p>Amongst these functionalities, recommendation is an existing feature of a few virtual assistants. To date, there is a wide range of literature resources. Most of the studies focus on certain aspects of virtual assistants’ recommendations, such as self-disclosure and reciprocity (Lee &amp; Choi, 2017). However, limited literature regards the virtual assistants’ recommendation as an independent factor and explores its effect on user performance (satisfaction, error, efforts) in different contexts. Neither did these researchers study user expectations when being recommended by virtual assistants. Therefore, in this proposal, both a quantitative study and a qualitative study are proposed for solving these two problems. The quantitative study looks at the effects of virtual assistants’ recommendations on user performance when users have different intentions. In other words, if the users have clear goals in mind. The qualitative study analyses the expectations that users have when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants. The quantitative study results can inspire interaction design by suggesting when it is a suitable circumstance for virtual assistants to recommend users<br>more options. The qualitative study results can help refine current design by considering the user expectations that have not been met. This proposal focuses on a scene where people use virtual assistants to select restaurants. This is to avoid the influence of confounding factors in other complicated scenes such as booking a flight or requesting an Uber ride. Accordingly, the proposal will be structured around answering the following two research questions: </p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Intention &amp; Recommendation Structure: Whether there is an effect of the user intention and the recommendation structure on the user performance (satisfaction, effort, error) when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants.</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    Expectation: What are users’ expectations when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants in different intentions?</em></p>
<p>Given the two research questions above, the study will employ a mixture of methods. The first research question is studied by designing a mixed factorial experiment, which will be followed by a mixed design Analysis of Variance (ANOVA). Regarding user expectations, a semi-structured interview is designed before employing grounded theory to investigate the totality of this context. Afterwards, the merits and demerits of these studies will be discussed.</p>
<h3 id="Literature_Review">Literature Review</h3><p>A number of related literature exists on the topic of virtual assistants. Crestani and Du (2006) claim that spoken queries on mobile searches are longer but more “natural”. This finding showed the potential of dialogue-style interactions. Furthermore, a wide range of research focuses on the use of virtual assistants, including the feature of recommendations. Smyth et al. (2004) studied how to rely on user preference and needs to automatically generate compound critiques that can be presented to the user, whereas Matejka et al. (2009) researched the algorithms and succeeded in increasing the number of good recommendations by 2.1 times. </p>
<p>However, little work involves user intention and the recommendation effects on user performance. An exception is Kang et al. (2017), who investigated how users deploy natural language to ask for recommendations. In this study, the taxonomy was employed and the user goals were divided into three levels: navigational, informational and transactional. The follow-up queries were applied and surprisingly, the finding showed that the user employed a ‘critiquing style’ when refining the initial request. Additionally, the users were more likely to query with deep features when speaking as opposed to texting. This indicated the imperfection of current systems and the potential of the conversational assistant. Similarly, Chai et al. (2002) compared the menu-driven system with the natural language system, and found that the number of clicks and average time were reduced by 63.2 percent and 33.3 percent respectively – the efficiency and promise of the natural language system were demonstrated in the research.</p>
<p>Regarding user intention, Lee and Choi (2017) proposed the research question as “How does self-disclosure and reciprocity between a user and a conversational assistant affect user satisfaction and intention to use?”. He found that self-disclosure and reciprocity were paramount factors that affect user satisfaction. Furthermore, the interactional enjoyment and the feeling of trust would make the recommendations more believable and persuasive. Although the above factors can lead to intention to use, the study lacks the research on the original intention of users. Therefore, in this proposal, the effects of user goals and recommendation structures will be discussed. The methods of follow-up queries used by Kang et al. (2017) can be applied in this proposal. </p>
<p>There are also several related works relevant to the evaluation of satisfaction of using virtual assistants. Kiseleva et al. (2016) divided the structured search dialogue into two groups that were single task search dialogue and multi-task search dialogue. Defined by Kiseleva et al. (2016), the multi-task search dialogue consists of multiple interactions with the intelligent assistant that lead towards one final goal. This proposal focuses on the particular context that selects restaurants, which is the multi-task search dialogue. Therefore, a set of analysing methods that are related to these types of interactions can be employed. Kiseleva et al. (2016) proposed an equation that evaluates the satisfaction of users:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Equation 1: SAT(T1,…,Tm) = h(I(T1,…,Tm)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This evaluation describes a function h that, given a set of interaction signals, would predict user satisfaction (SAT). T1, … , Tm means the tasks in the multi-task search dialogue, while I(T) describes the combination of a set of interaction signals in the tasks (Kiseleva et al., 2016). This method shows 71% to 81% over the baseline in Kiseleva’s (2016) study. Additionally, the follow-up queries with a five-point Likert scale were also employed in Kiseleva’s (2016) research. These two methods can also be used in this proposal due to accuracy and acceptance. Although Jiang et al. (2015) modelled the action patterns and assessed the SAT by proposing the equation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Equation 2: P(v|s,u) = (c(s,u,v)+α·Pml(v|u)+β·Pml(v))/Σvi∈U c(s,u,vi)+α+β</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This equation is too complicated and consists of numerous actions factors. Therefore, only Equation 1 will be used in this proposal. </p>
<h3 id="Quantitative_Study">Quantitative Study</h3><h4 id="Method">Method</h4><h5 id="Participants">Participants</h5><p>A total of 30 participants are projected to be recruited through the Internet, including via emails, social networks and so forth. The participants should be recruited only when they meet two conditions. To be specific, they should not only have a good command of English but also should be familiar with using digital devices. In other words, those who have never used smartphones or cannot speak English will not be recruited. After the experiment, a £10 gift card will be reimbursed as a reward. </p>
<h5 id="Design">Design</h5><p>A factorial experiment will be employed. The primary independent variables are user goal and recommendation structure. User goal is a within-subject factor. It denotes whether the user has a clear goal in mind. For example, “Find a Japanese restaurant around me” will be a vague goal, in contrast to a clear goal like, “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30”. As for the recommendation structure, it is a between-subject factor that refers to three different types of recommendation design. In terms of dependent variables, the five-point Likert scale results, completion time, completion rate, the number of queries and clicks, dwell time and Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) rate will be collected during the experiment. These variables measure the error rate, effort, efficiency and throughput. </p>
<h5 id="Material">Material</h5><p>In order to prepare the particular task for this experiment, a virtual assistant prototype will be developed. The prototype should be able to use natural language to interact with users. There also should be a Graphical User Interface (GUI) that displays the list of results whenever users request. The prototype has three different modes explained by flowcharts (a), (b) and (c). The participants from three groups will experience these modes respectively. Flowchart (a) only provides a list of restaurants from which users can select, whereas flowchart (b) and (c) can recommend the user options. The difference between flowchart (b) and (c) is that flowchart (b) provides the recommendation when users are dissatisfied, while flowchart (c) recommends after users have selected one restaurant. In flowchart (b) and flowchart (c), the recommended item should be better than the item the user selects at some aspects (price, distance, etc.).</p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/iuaPSnu.png" alt="Figure 1. (a) User flow without recommendations, (b) User flow with recommendations after dissatisfaction, (c) User flow with recommendations after satisfaction" title="Figure 1. (a) User flow without recommendations, (b) User flow with recommendations after dissatisfaction, (c) User flow with recommendations after satisfaction"></p>
<h5 id="Procedure">Procedure</h5><p>There will be a two-minute introduction at the beginning of the experiment. This is to introduce the prototype’s basic functions and to inform participants how to use the multi-task search dialogue. After introducing the virtual assistant, a trial task around selecting restaurants will be conducted before the formal experiment. The trial task is aimed at allowing participants to be familiar with the virtual assistants. During the trial task, participants can choose from numerous example query questions that are presented. These questions range from generally asking for restaurants to asking for a particular distance or price. For example, “Find a Japanese restaurant around me” is a general question, but “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30” contains more detail.</p>
<p>Then the 30 participants will be divided randomly into three groups, each group consisting of 10 people. These three groups will conduct the above three user flows separately. Each participant will conduct the experiment twice with different goals. The first time the participants are assigned to the vague goal that is “Find a Japanese restaurant around me”, the following prompt will be presented.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Imagine that, at this moment, you would like to have dinner in a Japanese restaurant, and that you are about to use a virtual assistant to select one Japanese restaurant, but you do not have very clear criteria for selection. Please use natural language to interact with the virtual assistant, the virtual assistant may give you many choices. If so, select one that suits you most. </em></p>
<p>For the second time, they are assigned a clear goal that is “Find a Japanese restaurant within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30”, and the following prompt will be presented.</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Imagine that, at this moment, you are about to use a virtual assistant to select one Japanese restaurant, but this time you have very clear criteria for selection, you would prefer one that is within 0.5 miles with an average price below £30. Please use natural language to interact with the virtual assistant, the virtual assistant may give you many choices, if so, select one that suits you most.
</em></p>
<p>During the experiment, the users’ steps, completion time, number of queries and clicks, dwell time and ASR rate will be collected. After completing the task, all participants will be asked to use the five-point Likert scale to answer the following questions:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    How satisﬁed are you with your experience in this task in general?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    How satisﬁed are you with your experience in each subtask?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    How satisﬁed are you with the final restaurant you selected?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4)    Did you put in a lot of effort to complete the task</em></p>
<p>Regarding the participants in the group with the recommendation, they are required to answer the additional question:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5)    How satisﬁed are you with the recommendation?
</em></p>
<h4 id="Data_Analysis_Plan">Data Analysis Plan</h4><p>The quantitative study deals with the research question about the effects of user goal and recommendation structure on user performance. Because this study is a factorial design, a mixed design ANOVA will be employed to analyse the effects. Regarding the users’ intention, this independent variable has two levels – the vague goal and the clear goal separately. In terms of the effects of the recommendation of virtual assistants, three dependent factors should be paid attention: efforts, error rate and satisfaction. </p>
<p>Initially, the data that involves the severe failure of automatic speech recognition should be excluded. The trials in which users request three times but have not completed the goal should be excluded. This is to decrease the influence of the error on user satisfaction. Secondly, in order to measure the main factors, several measure methods will be utilised. As for the efforts, this factor can be measured by the steps, completion time. Also, the result of five-point Likert scale that corresponds with the question “Did you put in a lot of effort to complete the task?” can measure the efforts. The error can be measured by ASR rate and completion rate. The degree of satisfaction can be measured by the result of five-point Likert scale that involves querying satisfaction. Additionally, Equation 1 that was proposed by Julia Kiseleva (2016) can also measure satisfaction. Therefore, there will be two ways of evaluating satisfaction, the five-point Likert scale and Equation 1. The reason for using two methods is to improve accuracy. What the participants answered may not be consistent with what they really thought, thus the quantified data can reveal such consistency when comparing the two data sets. </p>
<p>Furthermore, a 2x3 repeated measures ANOVA on the participants’ satisfaction value will be run to investigate the effects of the user intention recommendation structure on user satisfaction. By means of comparing the P value with 0.05, the following question can be answered: </p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Whether there is a significant main effect of the user intention on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    Whether there is a significant main effect of the recommendation structure on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    Whether there is a significant interaction effect of user intention × recommendation structure on user satisfaction when using virtual assistants in the context of restaurant selection</em></p>
<p>As the effort the user puts in can be one of the attributes of user satisfaction, a similar 2x3 repeated measures ANOVA on the participants’ effort value can be run to investigate the effects of user intention recommendation structure on the user workload. Accordingly, the similar three questions can be answered. Regarding the error rate, the similar practice can be applied.</p>
<p>Additionally, as there are two sets of user satisfaction that are calculated by Equation 1 and 5-point Likert scale, the results of two methods of evaluating efforts and satisfaction should be compared. If they are different to a large extent, the procedure and analysis should require an in-depth investigation, in which way the accuracy can be enhanced.  </p>
<h3 id="Qualitative_Study">Qualitative Study</h3><h4 id="Method-1">Method</h4><h5 id="Participants-1">Participants</h5><p>Ten participants will take part in the study, these participants will be the subset of participants from the quantitative study. Amongst them, five people will be the participants who have interacted with the system that recommended before selection, whereas the other five participants will be the people who have interacted with the system that recommended after selection. </p>
<h5 id="Procedure-1">Procedure</h5><p>The participants will be asked to have an interview after the quantitative experiment. During the quantitative experiment, the researchers should take notes when observing the participants who are about to be interviewed. These notes are aimed at providing insight that allows researchers to ask relevant and valuable questions during the interview. The interview will be semi-structured, this is to ensure a certain degree of freedom and to focus on the research question. The questions can be adjusted based on what the researchers have observed. The research question of the qualitative study is “What are users’ expectations when selecting restaurants with virtual assistants in different intentions (clear goal or vague goal)?” Therefore, around the topic “expectation”, the interview will include the following eight main questions. The questions can also be changed according to the situation:</p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>1)    Did you complete the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>2)    How much effort did you put into the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>3)    How satisfied are you with your final selection?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4)    Did you have any obstacles when doing the task? </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>4.1)    If yes, what obstacles did you have during the task?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5)    How satisfied are you with the recommendation?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5.1)    If yes, do you have any expectations when using it?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>5.2).    If no, why are you dissatisfied with it, any suggestions?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>6)    Do you have expectations when you use the virtual assistant?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>7)    Is there any difference between the recommendation and your expectation?</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>8)    Do you have any comments about the virtual assistants?</em></p>
<p>The interview will be audio recorded and transcribed later. The researchers are also required to take notes during the interview if the answer is regarded to be important. In terms of interviewees’ answers, if it is insightful, the researcher should ask for an explanation, especially the questions around attitude towards the recommendation. Some participants may select the restaurant that is consistent with the recommendation, some may not. Therefore, the interview questions should be adjusted to discover the deeper reason why they follow the recommendation or not. For example, the user may be dissatisfied with the recommendation because they feel offended or interrupted. The interview time will be limited to 60 minutes. These participants will be reimbursed with a £10 gift card at the end of the interview.</p>
<h4 id="Data_Analysis_Plan-1">Data Analysis Plan</h4><p>The grounded theory will be employed to analyse the data. A three-stage analysis will be employed. Open Coding is the first stage, when the audio will be transcribed. In the transcript, the important small chunks of text should be coded and the keywords and quotes should be marked. More specifically, the words about satisfaction, expectation, obstacles and suggestions should be paid more attention, especially the words that describe the gap between what the users expect and what the virtual assistant actually responds. </p>
<p>The following stage is the Axial Coding, when the correlation amongst those keywords is expected to be found. There will be some relationships between the satisfaction and the obstacles, as the obstacles can account for dissatisfaction. Similarly, the expectation can be related to satisfaction and obstacles, as the satisfaction and obstacles reveal the demerits and improvement of current virtual assistant design. </p>
<p>The final stage is the Selective Coding, where the most frequent keywords or categories should be paid attention to. This is because these frequent concepts have more weight more than other factors. By investigating these frequent factors, a link that can hold all categories together is projected to be found, in which way the common expectation that users have when asking virtual assistants for recommendations will be concluded.</p>
<h3 id="Discussion">Discussion</h3><p>The results of both the quantitative study and the qualitative study will have implications for designing the interaction of virtual assistant. As for the quantitative study, if there is a significant main effect of user intention on user satisfaction, it can be concluded that the designers should apply different strategies to deal with different user goals. Additionally, the results can indicate the suitable recommendation structure in a different context. If there is a significant main effect of the recommendation structure on the user satisfaction, the designer should refer to the recommendation structure that has better user performance: higher satisfaction, lower error rate and effort. Furthermore, the interaction effect of user intention × recommendation structure suggests the suitable recommendation form for virtual assistants when the users have different goals. </p>
<p>One merit of the quantitative study is the factorial design. This design is more efficient than one-factor-at-a-time experiments, and can reveal the interaction effect. Additionally, the within-subject design in the user goal decreases the number of trials, whereas the between-subjects design in recommendation decreases the “carryover effects”, which means that “user participation in one condition may affect performance in other conditions” (Ludlow &amp; Gutierrez, 1976). In terms of the demerits, although the accuracy can be improved by employing two evaluations methods (Equation 1 and five-point Likert scale), such practice takes plenty of time. Additionally, the requirement of the prototype is high, in order to allow users to experience three types of the recommendation structures and the development of the prototype will probably be time-consuming and money-consuming. Additionally, the failure of recognizing the audio can be the confounding variable, so the prototype should be highly capable of recognizing audio. This increases the workload of developing. The reason for not using existing virtual assistants such as Siri and Cortana is the inconvenience of their fixed structure. In other words, employing prototypes have much more flexibility. Although Klemmer et al. (2000) proposed the Wizard of Oz prototyping tool for speech user interface, this proposal suggests using an actual VA. The reason is that employing this prototype can have better ecological validity than using the Wizard of Oz. Therefore, it is necessary to employ the actual virtual assistant. Furthermore, as there are plenty of open-source virtual assistant APIs online, the difficulty of developing can be decreased. </p>
<p>Regarding the qualitative study, the current obstacles to the recommendations of virtual assistants are expected to be found. This can help the designer to decrease the obstacles and improve user satisfaction. Also, user expectation suggests the improvement of virtual assistant design. Based on the gap between what the users expect and what the virtual assistant actually responds, designers can fulfil the user expectations better. The strength of the qualitative study is simplicity. The semi-structured interview does not require a complicated prototype, so it is easy to conduct and can generate a large amount of detail. However, the flexibility of semi-structured interview may decrease reliability. The participants’ answers can be too open to extract keywords. Furthermore, as the study relies on the grounded theory to investigate the interview data, this method helps develop an understanding of user expectations in  a context that is not pre-formed with existing theories (Engward, 2013). However, this method is often difficult to manage, because it requires many more insights and skills. It can be hard to link keywords together in theoretical models at the Selective Coding Stage. Finding a central category that holds everything together is not an easy task. Therefore, the difficulty in analysis and investigation is the weakness of this qualitative study.</p>
<h3 id="Limitations">Limitations</h3><p>The proposed study has a number of limitations. Firstly, the study is limited by the number of participants. This is due to the considerations of the cost of time and compensation. Secondly, the proposal is aimed at researching the recommendation effects for virtual assistants in the context of restaurants and it is unclear whether the same effects work for virtual assistants in other particular contexts. In other words, the external validity may not be high. Such limitation leaves space for future work. Furthermore, as participants from different groups may have different criteria about satisfaction when filling in the five-point Likert scale, this can be a confounding factor when investigating the effects of recommendation structure on user satisfaction. Although this problem can be avoided if the recommendation structure is a within-subject factor, such practice will make the participant repeatedly conduct the experiment six times, which significantly increases the workload of a single participant. As the participant may lose patience or feel tired after a few rounds, the data about user satisfaction will be influenced. Therefore, the current practice probably is a practicable trade-off. On the other hand, part of the participants will be required to take part in both the quantitative study and qualitative study, the experimental time can be more than one and half hour. In this case, participants may feel bored and impatient, leading to the inaccuracy of the data that researcher collected.</p>
<h3 id="References">References</h3><p>Chai, J., Horvath, V., Nicolov, N., Stys, M., Kambhatla, N., Zadrozny, W., &amp; Melville, P. (2002). Natural language assistant: A dialog system for online product recommendation. AI Magazine, 23(2), 63.</p>
<p>Crestani, F., &amp; Du, H. (2006). Written versus spoken queries: A qualitative and quantitative comparative analysis. Journal of the Association for Information Science and Technology, 57(7), 881-890.</p>
<p>Engward, H. (2013). Understanding grounded theory. Nursing Standard, 28(7), 37-41.</p>
<p>Jiang, J., Hassan Awadallah, A., Jones, R., Ozertem, U., Zitouni, I., Gurunath Kulkarni, R., &amp; Khan, O. Z. (2015, May). Automatic online evaluation of intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 24th International Conference on World Wide Web (pp. 506-516). International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee.</p>
<p>Kang, J., Condiff, K., Chang, S., Konstan, J. A., Terveen, L., &amp; Harper, F. M. (2017, August). Understanding How People Use Natural Language to Ask for Recommendations. In Proceedings of the Eleventh ACM Conference on Recommender Systems (pp. 229-237). ACM.</p>
<p>Kiseleva, J., Williams, K., Hassan Awadallah, A., Crook, A. C., Zitouni, I., &amp; Anastasakos, T. (2016, July). Predicting user satisfaction with intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 39th International ACM SIGIR conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (pp. 45-54). ACM.</p>
<p>Kiseleva, J., Williams, K., Jiang, J., Hassan Awadallah, A., Crook, A. C., Zitouni, I., &amp; Anastasakos, T. (2016, March). Understanding user satisfaction with intelligent assistants. In Proceedings of the 2016 ACM on Conference on Human Information Interaction and Retrieval (pp. 121-130). ACM.</p>
<p>Klemmer, S. R., Sinha, A. K., Chen, J., Landay, J. A., Aboobaker, N., &amp; Wang, A. (2000, November). Suede: a Wizard of Oz prototyping tool for speech user interfaces. In Proceedings of the 13th annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (pp. 1-10). ACM.</p>
<p>Lee, S., &amp; Choi, J. (2017). Enhancing user experience with conversational agent for movie recommendation: Effects of self-disclosure and reciprocity. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 103, 95-105.</p>
<p>Ludlow, A., &amp; Gutierrez, R. (2014). Developmental psychology. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan</p>
<p>Matejka, J., Li, W., Grossman, T., &amp; Fitzmaurice, G. (2009, October). CommunityCommands: command recommendations for software applications. In Proceedings of the 22nd annual ACM symposium on User interface software and technology (pp. 193-202). ACM.</p>
<p>Ozeki, M., Maeda, S., Obata, K., &amp; Nakamura, Y. (2009). Virtual assistant: enhancing content acquisition by eliciting information from humans. Multimedia Tools and Applications, 44(3), 433-448. </p>
<p>Rong, X., Fourney, A., Brewer, R. N., Morris, M. R., &amp; Bennett, P. N. (2017, May). Managing Uncertainty in Time Expressions for Virtual Assistants. In Proceedings of the 2017 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (pp. 568-579). ACM.</p>
<p>Smyth, B., McGinty, L., Reilly, J., &amp; McCarthy, K. (2004, September). Compound critiques for conversational recommender systems. In Web Intelligence, 2004. WI 2004. Proceedings. IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on (pp. 145-151). IEEE.</p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This proposal introduces an experimental method to manage recommendation and explore the use of virtual assistants in the context of a restaurant, and got a distinction mark.<br>]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/HCI/"/>
    
      <category term="Research" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Research/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Digital Story - What is HCI?]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/09/25/hci1/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/09/25/hci1/</id>
    <published>2017-09-24T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-10-16T16:11:10.000Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a funny digital story explaining what is HCI, have fun guys! <a id="more"></a> (P.S. If you live in China, you might need VPN to watch the following video)</p>
<h5 id="What_is_HCI?">What is HCI?</h5><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QYTTFu1hvVA" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>This is a funny digital story explaining what is HCI, have fun guys!]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/HCI/"/>
    
      <category term="HCI" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/HCI/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[新华书店 & 公交车 - 碎片化阅读到一体化体验]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2017/02/16/portfolio4/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2017/02/16/portfolio4/</id>
    <published>2017-02-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:30:30.371Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>新华书店是一家历史悠久的传统书店。随着互联网的发展，人们读书的渠道变得多样化，对于实体书店的认识也发生变化。而这份交互设计作品集，则专注于帮助实体书店在互联网时代重新定位自己的发展方向，以获得用户更多的关注，提高自己的市场份额。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/Idutl45.png" alt="新华书店 &amp; 公交车" title="新华书店 &amp; 公交车"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>新华书店是一家历史悠久的传统书店。随着互联网的发展，人们读书的渠道变得多样化，对于实体书店的认识也发生变化。而这份交互设计作品集，则专注于帮助实体书店在互联网时代重新定位自己的发展方向，以获得用户更多的关注，提高自己的市场份额。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[Wecoo - 轻量化小团队协作工具]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/30/portfolio3/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/30/portfolio3/</id>
    <published>2015-10-30T00:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:30:13.105Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>wecoo是由我负责管理的一个团队共同完成的一个课程设计，这是一款针对小团体的以信息交流为主的轻量级团队协作移动端应用，wecoo取自we cooperate，中文名是微酷，其针对的目标用户也是兴趣团体、学生组织和社团等小团队。摈弃了文件传输、文件共享等等复杂功能之后，轻量化的wecoo更能给小团体增添活力。<a id="more"></a>在整个产品设计过程中，我是负责产品和团队的管理，参与其中每个流程，负责每个环节的落实，而其中我最主要负责的还是线框图、交互设计、原型设计这几个方面。</p>
<p>wecoo是一款轻量级的团队协作应用，因此在功能上我做了特别多的把控，把文件类的功能全部砍掉，因为这一不适合移动端，二不适用小团体。大的团队一般是以文件为主要协作方式，比如我画了原型给设计师，设计师按原型画设计稿，然后再交付给工程师，这一整个流程都是以文件为主，而学生团体、兴趣团体更多是开会、活动、聚餐等等，这是一种以信息为主的协作方式，因此wecoo针对这类目标用户提出了5种信息流：任务、会议、活动、公告、投票，用这5种信息流来作为团队的协作方式。考虑到wecoo的目标用户分为团队管理者和团队成员，因此wecoo增添了贡献度来辅助管理者进行考勤，并且，wecoo对管理者和成员的呈现方式也略为不同，发起信息流的管理者可以对信息内容进行再编辑，也可以更改成员权限或添加新成员，但成员手中的wecoo是看不到这些icon的，因此更不会对其进行操作，所以这样能做到针对不同用户做到不同层次的简化，使得管理者和成员看到的都是针对他们情况的最简产品。同时，wecoo的团队账单增加了团队账务的透明度，会议和活动的盖楼讨论增添了团队的活力，因此wecoo在很多层面考虑了小团队用户的用户体验。并且，我在wecoo的交互上做了很多提升，比如3D Touch的peek的应用，长按日期快速添加的交互应用，利用系统提醒减少深层级操作的交互应用，这使得用户点击即可查看新成员申请、请假信息、完成任务通知等等，这相当于把深层级的页面提前，从而减少用户的操作流程，即使用户不知道那些深层级的页面，也不需要用户学习，这极大的降低用户的认知负担。</p>
<p>这些交互上的体验一张作品集的图片展现不出来，如果大家想看的话，可以点击<a href="http://ursocute.github.io/wecoo/wecoo2/iphone5s.html" target="_blank" rel="external">交互式原型</a>，来查看上述的交互细节和动效设计，如果还想了解具体的设计流程的话，还可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1pJCHvsf" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>。</p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/nd9kQUK.jpg" alt="wecoo" title="wecoo"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>wecoo是由我负责管理的一个团队共同完成的一个课程设计，这是一款针对小团体的以信息交流为主的轻量级团队协作移动端应用，wecoo取自we cooperate，中文名是微酷，其针对的目标用户也是兴趣团体、学生组织和社团等小团队。摈弃了文件传输、文件共享等等复杂功能之后，轻量化的wecoo更能给小团体增添活力。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[UI.cn - UI中国iOS版设计初探]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/18/portfolio2/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/18/portfolio2/</id>
    <published>2015-10-17T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:29:44.046Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>一直很喜欢UI.cn这个网站，有次偶然的机会，我用iPhone的Safari打开UI.cn的时候，发现许多页面并未做成响应式，非常不方便阅读，我再一想，连站酷都有iOS版的，UI中国应该也有iOS版的吧，所以我就跑去App Store里搜，结果什么也没有，这个时候我就萌生了设计UI.cn iOS版的交互原型的想法，做好之后还能放进自己的作品集里。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>我在深入了解了UI中国之后，发现UI中国是以内容为主、浏览学习为主的一个网站，它同时也提供招聘、 找工作、图书推荐、话题社区等服务，但这类服务多为辅，比如话题社区，整页整页都是0回复，因此考虑了这些因素后，我在做UI.cn iOS版的交互时就着重注意了移动端内容阅读的用户体验，把用户偶尔使用的招聘、私信等等功能都放进了层级稍深的抽屉式导航里。而上传作品、上传经验等功能则全部去掉，因为这些功能一不适合移动端，二对用户来说使用频率也不大，因此去掉反而能使应用更加轻便更加易用。总体来说，我个人还蛮喜欢这样的设计的，大家如果感兴趣的话还可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1jGfH46y" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>看一看。</p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/9BWaDtK.jpg" alt="UI.cn iOS" title="UI.cn iOS"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>一直很喜欢UI.cn这个网站，有次偶然的机会，我用iPhone的Safari打开UI.cn的时候，发现许多页面并未做成响应式，非常不方便阅读，我再一想，连站酷都有iOS版的，UI中国应该也有iOS版的吧，所以我就跑去App Store里搜，结果什么也没有，这个时候我就萌生了设计UI.cn iOS版的交互原型的想法，做好之后还能放进自己的作品集里。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title><![CDATA[漫生活 - 轻量级短漫UGC社区]]></title>
    <link href="http://yoursite.com/2015/10/06/portfolio1/"/>
    <id>http://yoursite.com/2015/10/06/portfolio1/</id>
    <published>2015-10-05T23:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-13T19:29:17.554Z</updated>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>想当交互设计师，最近就准备了一下自己的交互设计作品集，也不是很确定作品集具体是要做成什么样子，参考了知乎里<a href="http://www.zhihu.com/question/19977449/answer/48279051" target="_blank" rel="external">「交互设计师的简历和作品集应该怎么做才好」</a>这篇的格式，然后按照一般的设计流程完成了角色创建、功能架构、交互设计这几个方面。<a id="more"></a></p>
<p>这个产品是我自己构想的，是一个以短篇漫画创作为核心的社区型兼工具型的移动应用，App名叫漫生活，用户只需简单几步就可以创作属于自己的短篇漫画，而用户创作出来的作品叫漫书，相同类型相同话题的漫书放在一起形成漫圈。为了降低用户的学习成本，减少用户的创作流程，创作漫书的过程以模板创作为主，自由创作为辅，创作过程还可以随时保存随时预览，非常方便，完成之后会提供多种分享方式，系统还会根据用户选择的模板提供符合的标签，用户勾选后则发布到相应的漫圈中，与漫友形成互动，构成内容-创作的良性循环。因为这款App是社区型兼工具型的应用，而工具型应用变现能力非常有限，因此我着重突显了应用的社区性，在首页的发现、关注里大面积的推广热门的漫圈和漫书，比如及时推出“叶良辰”的模板和“叶良辰”的漫圈，以高质量的漫书内容和新近的热点话题来激发用户的参与欲与创作欲，从而不断的延长产品的生命，增加App的活跃度。我自己认为这是一款挺有意思的构想，大家有兴趣的话可以看一看，如果还想了解具体的角色创建、功能架构和交互设计，可以点击下载<a href="http://pan.baidu.com/s/1dDjVyY9" target="_blank" rel="external">源文件</a>。</p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/xlTCTMC.jpg" alt="漫生活" title="漫生活"></p>
]]></content>
    <summary type="html">
    <![CDATA[<p>想当交互设计师，最近就准备了一下自己的交互设计作品集，也不是很确定作品集具体是要做成什么样子，参考了知乎里<a href="http://www.zhihu.com/question/19977449/answer/48279051">「交互设计师的简历和作品集应该怎么做才好」</a>这篇的格式，然后按照一般的设计流程完成了角色创建、功能架构、交互设计这几个方面。]]>
    
    </summary>
    
      <category term="UX" scheme="http://yoursite.com/tags/UX/"/>
    
      <category term="Portfolio" scheme="http://yoursite.com/categories/Portfolio/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
